[
  {
    "question": "Which  is not a toxemic  infection ?",
    "options": [
      "relapsing fever",
      "tetanus",
      "gas gangrene",
      "botulism",
      "diphtheria"
    ],
    "correct": "relapsing fever"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  is not a toxemic  infection ?",
    "options": [
      "psittacosis",
      "tetanus",
      "gas gangrene",
      "botulism",
      "diphtheria"
    ],
    "correct": "psittacosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  is a toxemic  infection ?",
    "options": [
      "botulism",
      "psittacosis",
      "typhus",
      "tuberculosis"
    ],
    "correct": "botulism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a toxemic infection?",
    "options": [
      "diphtheria",
      "psittacosis",
      "typhus",
      "tuberculosis"
    ],
    "correct": "diphtheria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  is a toxemic  infection ?",
    "options": [
      "tetanus",
      "relapsing fever",
      "gonorrhea",
      "syphilis"
    ],
    "correct": "tetanus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which genus does not have coiled bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "Francisella",
      "Treponema",
      "Borellia",
      "Campylobacter",
      "Leptospira"
    ],
    "correct": "Francisella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which genus does not have coiled bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "Streptococcus",
      "Treponema",
      "Borrelia",
      "Campylobacter",
      "Leptospira"
    ],
    "correct": "Streptococcus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which genus does not have coiled bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "Neisseria",
      "Treponema",
      "Borellia",
      "Campylobacter",
      "Leptospira"
    ],
    "correct": "Neisseria"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteria of this genus are coiled:",
    "options": [
      "Treponema",
      "Streptococcus",
      "Staphylococcus",
      "Shigella",
      "Neisseria"
    ],
    "correct": "Treponema"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteria of this genus are coiled :",
    "options": [
      "Leptospira",
      "Streptococcus",
      "Staphylococcus",
      "Shigella",
      "Neisseria"
    ],
    "correct": "Leptospira"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "scarlet fever",
      "rabies",
      "yellow fever",
      "chicken pox",
      "tick-borne encephalitis"
    ],
    "correct": "scarlet fever"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "pertussis",
      "rabies",
      "hemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome",
      "chicken pox",
      "tick-borne encephalitis"
    ],
    "correct": "pertussis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "relapsing fever",
      "rabies",
      "yellow fever",
      "measles",
      "tick-borne encephalitis"
    ],
    "correct": "relapsing fever"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "anthrax",
      "influenza",
      "yellow fever",
      "chicken pox",
      "tick-borne encephalitis"
    ],
    "correct": "anthrax"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "syphilis",
      "infectious mononucleosis",
      "yellow fever",
      "chicken pox",
      "tick-borne encephalitis"
    ],
    "correct": "syphilis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "typhoid fever",
      "rabies",
      "yellow fever",
      "chicken pox",
      "rubella"
    ],
    "correct": "typhoid fever"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "Q-fever",
      "poliomyelitis",
      "yellow fever",
      "Crimean -Congo hemorrhagic fever",
      "tick-borne encephalitis"
    ],
    "correct": "Q-fever"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "Lyme  disease",
      "AIDS",
      "yellow fever",
      "smallpox",
      "tick-borne encephalitis"
    ],
    "correct": "Lyme  disease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "tularemia",
      "rubella",
      "measles",
      "chickenpox",
      "rabies"
    ],
    "correct": "tularemia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "parapertussis",
      "rabies",
      "yellow fever",
      "chickenpox",
      "tick-borne encephalitis"
    ],
    "correct": "parapertussis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is not a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "rabies",
      "scarlet fever",
      "pertussis",
      "typhus",
      "relapsing fever"
    ],
    "correct": "rabies"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is not a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "chickenpox",
      "typhoid fever",
      "pertussis",
      "typhus"
    ],
    "correct": "chickenpox"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is not a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "yellow fever",
      "Boutonneuse fever",
      "parapertussis",
      "relapsing fever"
    ],
    "correct": "yellow fever"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is not a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "tick-borne encephalitis",
      "meningococcal meningitis",
      "tuberculosis",
      "anthrax"
    ],
    "correct": "tick-borne encephalitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is not a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "rubella",
      "pertussis",
      "listeriosis",
      "Legionnaires’ disease"
    ],
    "correct": "rubella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  is not a bacterial  infection ?",
    "options": [
      "poliomyelitis",
      "syphilis",
      "gonorrhea",
      "typhus",
      "relapsing fever"
    ],
    "correct": "poliomyelitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is not a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "influenza",
      "tuberculosis",
      "diphtheria",
      "pertussis"
    ],
    "correct": "influenza"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is not a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "infectious mononucleosis",
      "meningococcal meningitis",
      "botulism",
      "gas gangrene"
    ],
    "correct": "infectious mononucleosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is not a bacterial infection?",
    "options": [
      "mumps",
      "meningococcal meningitis",
      "relapsing fever",
      "tick-borne rickettsial disease"
    ],
    "correct": "mumps"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -positive rods are the bacteria of the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Clostridium",
      "Esherichia",
      "Salmonella",
      "Shigella",
      "Francisella"
    ],
    "correct": "Clostridium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -positive rods are the bacteria of the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Corynebacterium",
      "Esherichia",
      "Salmonella",
      "Shigella",
      "Francisella"
    ],
    "correct": "Corynebacterium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -positive rods are the bacteria of the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Mycobacterium",
      "Esherichia",
      "Salmonella",
      "Shigella",
      "Francisella"
    ],
    "correct": "Mycobacterium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -positive rods are the bacteria of the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Bacillus",
      "Treponema",
      "Salmonella",
      "Shigella",
      "Neisseria"
    ],
    "correct": "Bacillus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -negative rods are the bacteria of the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Esherichia",
      "Clostridium",
      "Mycobacterium",
      "Corynebacterium"
    ],
    "correct": "Esherichia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -negative rods are the bacteria of the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Salmonella",
      "Clostridium",
      "Corynebacterium",
      "Bacillus"
    ],
    "correct": "Salmonella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -negative rods are the bacteria of the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Bordetella",
      "Mycobacterium",
      "Corynebacterium",
      "Bacillus"
    ],
    "correct": "Bordetella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -negative rods are the bacteria of the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Francisella",
      "Mycobacterium",
      "Corynebacterium",
      "Bacillus"
    ],
    "correct": "Francisella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is administered in case of:",
    "options": [
      "anthrax",
      "relapsing fever",
      "gonorrhea",
      "psittacosis",
      "syphilis"
    ],
    "correct": "anthrax"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is administered in  case of:",
    "options": [
      "pertussis",
      "relapsing fever",
      "gonorrhea",
      "psittacosis",
      "syphilis"
    ],
    "correct": "pertussis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is administered in case of:",
    "options": [
      "diphtheria",
      "paratyphoid fever",
      "gonorrhea",
      "mycoplasmosis",
      "candidiasis"
    ],
    "correct": "diphtheria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is administered in case of:",
    "options": [
      "tetanus",
      "listeriosis",
      "scarlet fever",
      "syphilis"
    ],
    "correct": "tetanus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is administered in case of:",
    "options": [
      "cholera",
      "gonorrhea",
      "Lyme disease",
      "Legionnaires’ disease"
    ],
    "correct": "cholera"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is not administered in case of:",
    "options": [
      "relapsing fever",
      "tularemia",
      "typhus",
      "anthrax",
      "typhoid fever"
    ],
    "correct": "relapsing fever"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is not administered in case of:",
    "options": [
      "syphilis",
      "diphtheria",
      "typhus",
      "pertussis",
      "typhoid fever"
    ],
    "correct": "syphilis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is not administered in case of:",
    "options": [
      "gonorrhea",
      "brucellosis",
      "plague",
      "tuberculosis"
    ],
    "correct": "gonorrhea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is not administered in case of:",
    "options": [
      "scarlet fever",
      "anthrax",
      "typhus",
      "tetanus"
    ],
    "correct": "scarlet fever"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is not administered in case of:",
    "options": [
      "borreliosis",
      "brucellosis",
      "typhoid fever",
      "diphteria"
    ],
    "correct": "borreliosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccination is not administered in case of:",
    "options": [
      "colibacillosis  (E.coli infection)",
      "brucellosis",
      "typhoid fever",
      "diphtheria"
    ],
    "correct": "colibacillosis  (E.coli infection)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -negative cocci are the bacteria of the genus:",
    "options": [
      "Veilonella",
      "Treponema",
      "Salmonella",
      "Shigella",
      "Corynebacterium"
    ],
    "correct": "Veilonella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -negative cocci are the bacteria of the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Neisseria",
      "Treponema",
      "Salmonella",
      "Shigella",
      "Corynebacterium"
    ],
    "correct": "Neisseria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -positive cocci are the bacteria of the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Streptococcus",
      "Treponema",
      "Shigella",
      "Corynebacterium",
      "Neisseria"
    ],
    "correct": "Streptococcus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gram -positive cocci are the bacteria of the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Staphylococcus",
      "Salmonella",
      "Shigella",
      "Corynebacterium",
      "Neisseria"
    ],
    "correct": "Staphylococcus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which genus of bacteria has H -antigen?",
    "options": [
      "Salmonella",
      "Staphylococcus",
      "Shigella",
      "Corynebacterium",
      "Neisseria"
    ],
    "correct": "Salmonella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  genus  of bacteria  has H-antigen ?",
    "options": [
      "Esherichia",
      "Staphylococcus",
      "Shigella",
      "Corynebacterium",
      "Neisseria"
    ],
    "correct": "Esherichia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  genus  of bacteria  has H-antigen?",
    "options": [
      "Vibrio",
      "Streptococcus",
      "Shigella",
      "Mycobacterium"
    ],
    "correct": "Vibrio"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  genus  of bacteria  does not have H-antigen ?",
    "options": [
      "Shigella",
      "Vibrio",
      "Salmonella",
      "Esherichia"
    ],
    "correct": "Shigella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  genus  of bacteria  does not have H-antigen?",
    "options": [
      "Streptococcus",
      "Vibrio",
      "Salmonella",
      "Esherichia"
    ],
    "correct": "Streptococcus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which genus of bacteria has K -antigen?",
    "options": [
      "Esherichia",
      "Corynebacterium",
      "Treponema",
      "Leptospira"
    ],
    "correct": "Esherichia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which genus of bacteria has K -antigen?",
    "options": [
      "Salmonella",
      "Corynebacterium",
      "Treponema",
      "Leptospira"
    ],
    "correct": "Salmonella"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteria of this genus are aerobes:",
    "options": [
      "Neisseria",
      "Shigella",
      "Salmonella",
      "Esherichia"
    ],
    "correct": "Neisseria"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteria of this genus are aerobes:",
    "options": [
      "Mycobacterium",
      "Shigella",
      "Salmonella",
      "Esherichia"
    ],
    "correct": "Mycobacterium"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteria of this genus are not facultative anaerobes:",
    "options": [
      "Neisseria",
      "Shigella",
      "Salmonella",
      "Esherichia"
    ],
    "correct": "Neisseria"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteria of this genus grow as R -colonies (rough) :",
    "options": [
      "Mycobacterium",
      "Shigella",
      "Salmonella",
      "Esherichia"
    ],
    "correct": "Mycobacterium"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteria of this genus grow as R -colonies (rough) :",
    "options": [
      "Yersinia",
      "Vibrio",
      "Streptococcus",
      "Salmonella"
    ],
    "correct": "Yersinia"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteria of this genus grow as R -colonies (rough) :",
    "options": [
      "Bacillus",
      "Bordetella",
      "Brucella",
      "Salmonella"
    ],
    "correct": "Bacillus"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteria of this genus grow as S -colonies (smooth) :",
    "options": [
      "Brucella",
      "Bacillus",
      "Mycobacterium",
      "Yersinia"
    ],
    "correct": "Brucella"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteria of this genus grow as S -colonies (smooth) :",
    "options": [
      "Esherichia",
      "Bacillus",
      "Mycobacterium",
      "Yersinia"
    ],
    "correct": "Esherichia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacter ioscopy is used in the diagnosing procedure of :",
    "options": [
      "gonorrhea",
      "Legionnaires’ disease",
      "colibacillosis (E.coli infection)",
      "brucellosis"
    ],
    "correct": "gonorrhea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacterioscopy is used in the diagnosing procedure of:",
    "options": [
      "syphilis",
      "Legionnaires’ disease",
      "listeriosis",
      "brucellosis"
    ],
    "correct": "syphilis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacterioscopy is used in the diagnosing procedure of:",
    "options": [
      "anthrax",
      "Legionnaires’ disease",
      "E.coli infection (escherichiosis)",
      "typhus"
    ],
    "correct": "anthrax"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacterioscopy is not used in the diagnosing procedure of:",
    "options": [
      "Legionnaires’ disease",
      "anthrax",
      "tuberculosis",
      "gas gangrene"
    ],
    "correct": "Legionnaires’ disease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacterioscopy is not used in the diagnosing procedure of:",
    "options": [
      "typhus",
      "relapsing fever",
      "meningococcal meningitis",
      "cholera"
    ],
    "correct": "typhus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacterioscopy is not used in the diagnosing procedure of:",
    "options": [
      "brucellosis",
      "anthrax",
      "plague",
      "cholera"
    ],
    "correct": "brucellosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A therapeutic  serum  is used to treat:",
    "options": [
      "diphtheria",
      "typhus",
      "relapsing fever",
      "cholera"
    ],
    "correct": "diphtheria"
  },
  {
    "question": "A therapeutic serum is used to treat:",
    "options": [
      "tetanus",
      "tuberculosis",
      "plague",
      "E.coli infection  (escherichiosis )"
    ],
    "correct": "tetanus"
  },
  {
    "question": "A therapeutic serum is used to treat:",
    "options": [
      "botulism",
      "brucellosis",
      "Lyme disease",
      "E.coli infection (escherichiosis)"
    ],
    "correct": "botulism"
  },
  {
    "question": "A skin test is used in the diagnosing procedure of:",
    "options": [
      "tuberculosis",
      "typhus",
      "relapsing fever",
      "meningococcal meningitis",
      "cholera"
    ],
    "correct": "tuberculosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A skin test is used in the diagnosing procedure of:",
    "options": [
      "anthrax",
      "syphilis",
      "listeriosis",
      "leptospirosis"
    ],
    "correct": "anthrax"
  },
  {
    "question": "A therapeutic  vaccine  is used to treat:",
    "options": [
      "gonorrhea",
      "tuberculosis",
      "plague",
      "E.coli infection (escherichiosis)"
    ],
    "correct": "gonorrhea"
  },
  {
    "question": "A therapeutic  serum  is used to treat:",
    "options": [
      "brucellosis",
      "diphtheria",
      "cholera",
      "paratyphoid fever"
    ],
    "correct": "brucellosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which infectious agent causes a highly hazardous infectious disease?",
    "options": [
      "Yersinia pestis",
      "Neisseria gonorrhoeae",
      "Leptospira  interrogans",
      "Haemophilus  influenzae"
    ],
    "correct": "Yersinia pestis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which infectious agent causes a highly hazardous infectious disease?",
    "options": [
      "Vibrio cholerae",
      "Shigella flexneri",
      "Clostridium  perfringens",
      "Bacteroides  fragilis"
    ],
    "correct": "Vibrio cholerae"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these infectious agents except one cause atypical pneumonia. Which one does not?",
    "options": [
      "Streptococcus pneumoniae",
      "Coxiella burnetii",
      "Legionella pneumophila",
      "Chlamydiophila  pneumonia"
    ],
    "correct": "Streptococcus pneumoniae"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dark -field microscopy  is used to study :",
    "options": [
      "Treponema pallidum",
      "Escherichia coli",
      "Rickettsia",
      "Staphylococcus",
      "Chlamydia"
    ],
    "correct": "Treponema pallidum"
  },
  {
    "question": "The spore -forming bacteria are:",
    "options": [
      "Clostridia",
      "Streptococci",
      "Neisseria",
      "Salmonella",
      "Corynebacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "Clostridia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which infectious agent causes relapsing fever ?",
    "options": [
      "Borrelia recurrentis",
      "Bordetella pertussis",
      "Salmonella typhi",
      "Rickettsia prowazekii",
      "Yersinia pestis"
    ],
    "correct": "Borrelia recurrentis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which infectious agent causes anthrax ?",
    "options": [
      "Bacillus anthracis",
      "Corynebacterium diphtheriae",
      "Bacteroides fragilis",
      "Klebsiella pneumoniae",
      "Pseudomonas aeruginosa"
    ],
    "correct": "Bacillus anthracis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The first -choice medicinal drug to treat a chlamydia infection is :",
    "options": [
      "azithromycin",
      "ampicillin",
      "nystatin",
      "gentamicin",
      "clindamycin"
    ],
    "correct": "azithromycin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which bacterium produces an enterotoxin?",
    "options": [
      "Vibrio cholerae",
      "Clostridium tetani",
      "Corynebacterium diphtheriae",
      "Bacillus  anthracis"
    ],
    "correct": "Vibrio cholerae"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to its mechanism of action related to a target cell the Botulinum toxin is:",
    "options": [
      "a blocker of a nerve  signal transmission",
      "an inhibitor of protein synthesis",
      "an activator of the adenylate cyclase system",
      "exfoliatin",
      "hemolysin"
    ],
    "correct": "a blocker of a nerve  signal transmission"
  },
  {
    "question": "The diphtheria toxin is :",
    "options": [
      "a histotoxin",
      "an endotoxin",
      "a neurotoxin",
      "an enterotoxin",
      "a leukocidin"
    ],
    "correct": "a histotoxin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which are viral infections?",
    "options": [
      "yellow fever and tick -borne encephalitis",
      "Lyme disease and scarlet fever",
      "pertussis and meningococcal meningiti s",
      "psittacosis and typhus"
    ],
    "correct": "yellow fever and tick -borne encephalitis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which are not viral infections?",
    "options": [
      "Lyme disease and scarlet fever",
      "mumps and measles",
      "rabies and poliomyelitis",
      "yellow fever and tick-borne encephalitis"
    ],
    "correct": "Lyme disease and scarlet fever"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a characteristic feature of both chlamydia and rickettsia?",
    "options": [
      "obligate intracellular parasitism",
      "disjunctive  reproduction",
      "ability to accumulate glycogen",
      "the presence of elementary bodies"
    ],
    "correct": "obligate intracellular parasitism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which scientist is the founder of the  physiological approach in microbiology?",
    "options": [
      "L. Pasteur",
      "A. van Leeuwenhoek",
      "L.A. Zilber",
      "P. Ehrlich",
      "D. I. Ivanovsky"
    ],
    "correct": "L. Pasteur"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which scientist is the founder of the physiological approach in microbiology?",
    "options": [
      "R .Koch",
      "I. I. Mechnikov",
      "P. Ehrlich",
      "A.A. Smorodintsev",
      "N.A. Krasilnikov"
    ],
    "correct": "R .Koch"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which scientist is the founder of immunology?",
    "options": [
      "I.I. Mechnikov",
      "L. Pasteur",
      "L.A. Zilber",
      "R.Koch",
      "D. I. Ivanovsky"
    ],
    "correct": "I.I. Mechnikov"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which scientist is the founder of immunology?",
    "options": [
      "P. Ehrlich",
      "E. Jenner",
      "H.M. Temin",
      "A. van Leeuwenhoek",
      "N.A. Krasilnikov"
    ],
    "correct": "P. Ehrlich"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who  discovered  microbes ?",
    "options": [
      "A. van Leeuwenhoek",
      "Hippocrates",
      "Lucretius",
      "L. Pasteur",
      "R.Koch"
    ],
    "correct": "A. van Leeuwenhoek"
  },
  {
    "question": "of microbiology?",
    "options": [
      "R.Koch",
      "A. van Leeuwenhoek",
      "L. Pasteur",
      "Z.V. Yermolyeva",
      "I.I. Mechnikov"
    ],
    "correct": "R.Koch"
  },
  {
    "question": "A. van Leeuwenhoek is known for:",
    "options": [
      "the invention of the first microscope",
      "the discovery of viruses",
      "the discovery of fermentation",
      "the discovery of phagocytosis",
      "producing a rabies vaccine"
    ],
    "correct": "the invention of the first microscope"
  },
  {
    "question": "Preventive  vaccines against the smallpox were firstly  invented by:",
    "options": [
      "E. Jenner",
      "L. Pasteur",
      "A. van Leeuwenhoek",
      "Hippocrates",
      "R. Koch ."
    ],
    "correct": "E. Jenner"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who discovered Vibrio cholera e?",
    "options": [
      "Koch",
      "Hansen",
      "Loeffler",
      "Pasteur",
      "Eberth"
    ],
    "correct": "Koch"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who discovered the typhoid bacillus?",
    "options": [
      "Eberth",
      "Hansen",
      "Loeffler",
      "Koch",
      "Pasteur"
    ],
    "correct": "Eberth"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who discovered the tuberculosis pathogen?",
    "options": [
      "R. Koch",
      "I.I. Mechnikov",
      "F. Loeffler",
      "L. Pasteur",
      "N.A. Krasilnikov"
    ],
    "correct": "R. Koch"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who introduced heating up to 120 ° С in a steam generator as a sterilization technique?",
    "options": [
      "L. Pasteur",
      "R. Koch",
      "Sh. Kitasato",
      "J. Lister",
      "N.I. Pirogov"
    ],
    "correct": "L. Pasteur"
  },
  {
    "question": "Fermentation was discovered by:",
    "options": [
      "L. Pasteur",
      "A. van Leeuwenhoek",
      "I.I. Mechnikov",
      "R.Koch",
      "D.I. Ivanovsky"
    ],
    "correct": "L. Pasteur"
  },
  {
    "question": "anthrax  and rabies?",
    "options": [
      "L. Pasteur",
      "A. van Leeuwenhoek",
      "I.I. Mechnikov",
      "R.Koch",
      "D.I. Ivanovsky"
    ],
    "correct": "L. Pasteur"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who introduced the theory of normal microflora?",
    "options": [
      "I.I. Mechnikov",
      "P.V. Tsiklinskaya",
      "L.G. Peretz",
      "R. Koch",
      "D.I. Ivanovsky"
    ],
    "correct": "I.I. Mechnikov"
  },
  {
    "question": "D.I. Ivanovsky is known for :",
    "options": [
      "the discovery of viruses",
      "the discovery of fermentation",
      "the invention of the first microscope",
      "the discovery of phagocytosis",
      "the production of the rabies vaccine"
    ],
    "correct": "the discovery of viruses"
  },
  {
    "question": "Louis  Pasteur  is known for :",
    "options": [
      "the production of the rabies vaccine",
      "the discovery of phagocytosis",
      "the introduction of the pure bacterial culture isolation technique",
      "the invention of the first microscope",
      "the discovery of viruses"
    ],
    "correct": "the production of the rabies vaccine"
  },
  {
    "question": "The microbial nature of fermentation was discovered by :",
    "options": [
      "L. Pasteur",
      "E. Haeckel",
      "R. Hooke",
      "I.I. Mechnikov",
      "R.Koch"
    ],
    "correct": "L. Pasteur"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who developed the production of attenuated (weakened) microorganisms strains?",
    "options": [
      "L. Pasteur",
      "E. Jenner",
      "R.Koch",
      "P. Ehrlich",
      "D. Bergey"
    ],
    "correct": "L. Pasteur"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who  introduced  the differential  staining  technique  based  on the cell wall composition ?",
    "options": [
      "H. Gram",
      "A. van Leeuwenhoek",
      "R.Koch",
      "L. Pasteur",
      "I.I. Mechnikov"
    ],
    "correct": "H. Gram"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who  discovered  antibiotics ?",
    "options": [
      "A. Fleming",
      "L. Pasteur",
      "R. Koch",
      "D.K. Zabolotny",
      "D.I. Ivanovsky"
    ],
    "correct": "A. Fleming"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who  introduced  chemotherapy first ?",
    "options": [
      "Ehrlich",
      "Domagk",
      "Woodson",
      "Pasteur"
    ],
    "correct": "Ehrlich"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteria are measured in :",
    "options": [
      "micrometres",
      "millimetres",
      "nanometres",
      "centimetres",
      "angstro ms"
    ],
    "correct": "micrometres"
  },
  {
    "question": "The resolving power of an optical microscope is :",
    "options": [
      "the capacity  to show the separate images of two points which are close together",
      "the capacity to observe the movement of an object",
      "the capacity to determine the size of an object",
      "the indicator of the refraction of the immersion system",
      "the indicator of the magnification of an object"
    ],
    "correct": "the capacity  to show the separate images of two points which are close together"
  },
  {
    "question": "The magnification of an optical microscope equals :",
    "options": [
      "the magnification of the objective lens multiplied by the magnification of the eyepiece",
      "the difference between the magnification of the objective lens and the magnification of the eyepiece",
      "the sum of the magnification of the objective lens and the magnification of the eyepiece",
      "the magnification of the objective lens",
      "the magnification of the eyepiece"
    ],
    "correct": "the magnification of the objective lens multiplied by the magnification of the eyepiece"
  },
  {
    "question": "The optical components of an optical microscope include everything except :",
    "options": [
      "tube",
      "condenser",
      "objective lens",
      "eyepiece",
      "collector"
    ],
    "correct": "tube"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  microorganisms  are gram -negativ e?",
    "options": [
      "meningococci",
      "streptococci",
      "corynebacteria",
      "actinomyces",
      "bacilli"
    ],
    "correct": "meningococci"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  microorganisms  are gram -negative ?",
    "options": [
      "gonococci",
      "staphylococci",
      "clostridia",
      "mycoplasma",
      "fungi"
    ],
    "correct": "gonococci"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  microorganisms  are gram -negative ?",
    "options": [
      "chlamydia",
      "pneumococci",
      "bifidobacteria",
      "mycobacteria",
      "actinomyces"
    ],
    "correct": "chlamydia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  microorganisms  are gram -positive ?",
    "options": [
      "streptococci",
      "meningococci",
      "borrelia",
      "Vibrio cholerae",
      "E.coli"
    ],
    "correct": "streptococci"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  microorganisms  are gram -positive ?",
    "options": [
      "mycobacteria",
      "chlamydia",
      "spirochetes",
      "gonococci",
      "mycoplasma"
    ],
    "correct": "mycobacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  microorganisms  are gram -positive ?",
    "options": [
      "pneumococci",
      "treponema",
      "shigella",
      "rickettsia ch",
      "gonococci"
    ],
    "correct": "pneumococci"
  },
  {
    "question": "The distinctive  feature  of gram -negative bacteria is :",
    "options": [
      "they stain red in the Gram -staining method",
      "there  are teichoic acids in their cell wall",
      "they stain the blue -violet in the Gram -staining method",
      "the basic component of their cell wall is a peptidoglycan",
      "there  are lipoteichoic acids in their cell wall"
    ],
    "correct": "they stain red in the Gram -staining method"
  },
  {
    "question": "The distinctive  feature  of gram -positive bacteria  is:",
    "options": [
      "they stain the blue -violet in the Gram -staining method",
      "they stain red in the Gram -staining method",
      "the basic component of their cell wall is a lipopolysaccharide",
      "their cell wall is O -antigen",
      "they do not have a multilayered peptidoglycan"
    ],
    "correct": "they stain the blue -violet in the Gram -staining method"
  },
  {
    "question": "The structure which prevents discoloration in gram -positive bacteria is a :",
    "options": [
      "cell wall",
      "outer membrane",
      "lipopolysaccharide",
      "plasma membrane",
      "capsule"
    ],
    "correct": "cell wall"
  },
  {
    "question": "The basic taxonomic unit in microbiology is :",
    "options": [
      "species",
      "kingdom",
      "class",
      "order",
      "family"
    ],
    "correct": "species"
  },
  {
    "question": "The basic taxon of prokaryotes is:",
    "options": [
      "species",
      "strain",
      "clone",
      "genus",
      "family"
    ],
    "correct": "species"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the proper order of taxonomic units from the largest to the smallest :",
    "options": [
      "kingdom, order, class, family, genus, species",
      "kingdom, species, family, class, order",
      "kingdom, family, order, genus, species",
      "kingdom, species, genus, family, class, order"
    ],
    "correct": "kingdom, order, class, family, genus, species"
  },
  {
    "question": "The basic  principle  of Bergey’s identification of bacteria is :",
    "options": [
      "according to the composition of the cell wall and Gram -staining",
      "according to the virulence degree",
      "according to the antibiotic sensitivity",
      "according to the relation to molecular oxygen",
      "according to the presence of the nucleus"
    ],
    "correct": "according to the composition of the cell wall and Gram -staining"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the strain of microorganisms?",
    "options": [
      "an identified pure culture of a certain microorganism species",
      "the total number of offspring which have been grown from one microbial cell",
      "the total number of bacteria which have grown on a growth medium",
      "the total number of bacteria which are visible during the microscopy of native material",
      "a population of microorganisms which inhabit one biotope"
    ],
    "correct": "an identified pure culture of a certain microorganism species"
  },
  {
    "question": "A clone  is:",
    "options": [
      "a genetically  homogenous pure culture of microorganisms which have originated from one cell",
      "a set of phenotypically and genetically similar strains of microbes",
      "an archival strain",
      "a set of microbes with low heterogeneity degree which have the same origin",
      "a population of one bacterial s pecies which has been grown on the same growth medium in an isolated colony"
    ],
    "correct": "a genetically  homogenous pure culture of microorganisms which have originated from one cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pure culture is a bacterial population of one :",
    "options": [
      "species",
      "morphovar",
      "biovar",
      "serotype",
      "chemotype"
    ],
    "correct": "species"
  },
  {
    "question": "A species is a population of microorganisms which are similar in everything except :",
    "options": [
      "sexual reproduction",
      "morphology",
      "biochemical activity",
      "antigenic properties",
      "pathogenicity"
    ],
    "correct": "sexual reproduction"
  },
  {
    "question": "A population  of microorganisms  which has been grown from one cell on a solid growth medium is a :",
    "options": [
      "colony",
      "strain",
      "biovar",
      "pure culture",
      "serotype"
    ],
    "correct": "colony"
  },
  {
    "question": "A population of microorganisms of one species is a :",
    "options": [
      "pure culture",
      "strain",
      "colony",
      "biovar",
      "serotype"
    ],
    "correct": "pure culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "A population of microorganisms produced from one microbial cell is a :",
    "options": [
      "clone",
      "strain",
      "colony",
      "pure culture",
      "phago var"
    ],
    "correct": "clone"
  },
  {
    "question": "A variation within a species of microorganisms is a/an:",
    "options": [
      "serotype",
      "strain",
      "clone",
      "isolate",
      "domain"
    ],
    "correct": "serotype"
  },
  {
    "question": "The basic shapes of microorganisms are :",
    "options": [
      "cocci, rods, spiral, branching",
      "bacilli, bacteria",
      "cocci, rods, mycoplasma",
      "diplococci, streptococci, staphylococci",
      "clostridia, bacilli"
    ],
    "correct": "cocci, rods, spiral, branching"
  },
  {
    "question": "Spiral bacteria include :",
    "options": [
      "borrelia",
      "bacilli",
      "actinomyces",
      "streptococci",
      "pseudomonas"
    ],
    "correct": "borrelia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Spiral bacteria include:",
    "options": [
      "spirilla",
      "clostridia",
      "mycobacteria",
      "staphylococci",
      "E. coli"
    ],
    "correct": "spirilla"
  },
  {
    "question": "Spiral bacteria include all the ones mentioned below except :",
    "options": [
      "rickettsia",
      "treponema",
      "borrelia",
      "leptospira"
    ],
    "correct": "rickettsia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Diplococci include :",
    "options": [
      "meningococci",
      "Preudomonas aeruginosa (blue -pus bacillus)",
      "bacilli",
      "mycobacteria",
      "shigella"
    ],
    "correct": "meningococci"
  },
  {
    "question": "Diplococci include :",
    "options": [
      "gonococci",
      "E.coli",
      "clostridia",
      "listeria",
      "staphylococci"
    ],
    "correct": "gonococci"
  },
  {
    "question": "All the bacteria mentioned below are rod -shaped except :",
    "options": [
      "streptococci",
      "bacilli",
      "clostridia",
      "coccobacteria",
      "enterobacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "streptococci"
  },
  {
    "question": "All the bacteria mentioned below are spherical except :",
    "options": [
      "coccobacteria",
      "staphylococci",
      "streptococci",
      "pneumococci",
      "sarcinae"
    ],
    "correct": "coccobacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which bacteria are arranged as grape -like clusters?",
    "options": [
      "staphylococci",
      "meningococci",
      "streptococci",
      "tetracocci",
      "pneumococci"
    ],
    "correct": "staphylococci"
  },
  {
    "question": "Streptoccci are :",
    "options": [
      "chain -forming cocci",
      "grape -like clusters of cocci",
      "packet -forming cocci",
      "defective cocci",
      "gram -negative cocci"
    ],
    "correct": "chain -forming cocci"
  },
  {
    "question": "Streptococci are:",
    "options": [
      "gram -positive cocci arranged in pairs and in a chain",
      "gram -negative cocci arranged in pairs and in a chain",
      "gram -positive cocci arranged as grape -like clusters",
      "gram -negative cocci arranged as grape -like clusters",
      "spore -forming gram -positive cocci"
    ],
    "correct": "gram -positive cocci arranged in pairs and in a chain"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sarcinae  are:",
    "options": [
      "packet -forming cocci",
      "grape -like clusters of cocci",
      "chain -forming cocci",
      "cocci arranged in pairs",
      "gram -negative cocci"
    ],
    "correct": "packet -forming cocci"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteria whose cells divide in two perpendicular planes forming packets of 8, 16, 32 bacteria are known as :",
    "options": [
      "sarcinae",
      "tetracocci",
      "micrococci",
      "staphylococci",
      "streptococci"
    ],
    "correct": "sarcinae"
  },
  {
    "question": "Diplococci are:",
    "options": [
      "cocci arranged in pairs",
      "cocci  arranged as grape -like clusters",
      "chain -forming cocci",
      "packet -forming cocci",
      "monococci"
    ],
    "correct": "cocci arranged in pairs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Staphylococci are :",
    "options": [
      "cocci arranged as grape -like clusters",
      "spiral cells with  8-12 coils",
      "chain -forming cocci",
      "cells which look like bent rods (comma -like shape)",
      "chain -forming rods"
    ],
    "correct": "cocci arranged as grape -like clusters"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vibrions are :",
    "options": [
      "cells which look like bent rods (comma -like shape)",
      "cocci arranged as grape -like clusters",
      "spiral cells with  8-12 coils",
      "chain -forming cocci",
      "chain -forming rods"
    ],
    "correct": "cells which look like bent rods (comma -like shape)"
  },
  {
    "question": "All the groups  of pathogens  mentioned  below  are infectious  for humans except:",
    "options": [
      "viroids",
      "viruses",
      "prions",
      "fungi",
      "bacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "viroids"
  },
  {
    "question": "Class Mollicutes  includes :",
    "options": [
      "mycoplasma",
      "rickettsia",
      "chlamydia",
      "spirochetes",
      "actinomyces"
    ],
    "correct": "mycoplasma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteria are :",
    "options": [
      "unicellular  prokaryotes",
      "multicellular prokaryotes",
      "unicellular eukaryotes",
      "multicellular  eukaryotes",
      "acellular"
    ],
    "correct": "unicellular  prokaryotes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Prokaryotic microorganisms include :",
    "options": [
      "spirochetes",
      "mold fungi",
      "viuses",
      "prions"
    ],
    "correct": "spirochetes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Prokaryotic microorganisms include :",
    "options": [
      "chlamydia",
      "yeasts of Candida  genus",
      "protozoa",
      "blue-green algae"
    ],
    "correct": "chlamydia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microorganisms studied by Microbiology are not prokaryotic?",
    "options": [
      "viruses",
      "actinomyces",
      "bacteria",
      "mycoplasma",
      "chlamydia"
    ],
    "correct": "viruses"
  },
  {
    "question": "The basic  structural  difference of eukaryotes is :",
    "options": [
      "a well -defined nucleus",
      "the presence of a cell wall",
      "peptidoglycan in the cell wall",
      "a nucleoid",
      "ribosomes 7 0S"
    ],
    "correct": "a well -defined nucleus"
  },
  {
    "question": "L-forms of bacteria are :",
    "options": [
      "the way to escape immune surveillance",
      "gram -positive",
      "formed under the influence of aminoglycosides",
      "the causative agents of acute infections",
      "sensitive to β-lactam antibiotics"
    ],
    "correct": "the way to escape immune surveillance"
  },
  {
    "question": "The morphological properties of bacteria are :",
    "options": [
      "shape, size, combination",
      "the capacity  to take up different stains",
      "the way they grow on growth  media",
      "conditions for culturing",
      "the presence of a nucleoid"
    ],
    "correct": "shape, size, combination"
  },
  {
    "question": "Plasmids :",
    "options": [
      "are extrachromosomal factor of heredity",
      "participate in the cell division",
      "are formed with accumulation of metabolites",
      "are intracellular inclusions",
      "are a virulence factor of microorganisms"
    ],
    "correct": "are extrachromosomal factor of heredity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sterilization  is:",
    "options": [
      "a complete  removal  of all the types of microorganisms and their spores from the objects of the environment",
      "a complete  removal  of all the pathogenic microorganisms from the objects of the environment",
      "a complete  removal  of all the potentially pathogenic (opportunistic) and pathogenic microorganisms from the",
      "objects of the environment",
      "a partial  removal  of all the pathogenic microorganisms from the objects of the environment"
    ],
    "correct": "a complete  removal  of all the types of microorganisms and their spores from the objects of the environment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Disinfection is :",
    "options": [
      "elimination of  pathogenic and potentially pathogenic (opportunistic)  microorganisms  on the objects  of the",
      "environment",
      "elimination of  pathogenic  microorganisms in the organs and tissues of the body",
      "elimination of  pathogenic microorga nisms and their spores",
      "elimination of  potentially pathogenic (opportunistic)  microorganisms  with chemical substances"
    ],
    "correct": "elimination of  pathogenic and potentially pathogenic (opportunistic)  microorganisms  on the objects  of the"
  },
  {
    "question": "Antibiotics  are:",
    "options": [
      "chemotherapeutic  substances  of natural , semi -synthetic  or synthetic  origin  which  in small  concentrations",
      "inhibit  the reproduction  or cause  the death  of sensitive  microorganisms  and tumor  cells inside  a macroorganism",
      "biologically  active  substances synthesized by plants",
      "antibiotic -like substances of bacterial origin which inhibit the reproduction of homologous and similar species",
      "chemotherapeutic substances of synthetic origin which in small concentration cause the inhibition or death of"
    ],
    "correct": "chemotherapeutic  substances  of natural , semi -synthetic  or synthetic  origin  which  in small  concentrations"
  },
  {
    "question": "A gene is a :",
    "options": [
      "fragment of DNA molecule",
      "specific protein",
      "chromosome",
      "nucleotide triplet",
      "plasmid"
    ],
    "correct": "fragment of DNA molecule"
  },
  {
    "question": "A genotype is the total number of :",
    "options": [
      "the gene of a bacterial cell",
      "all the traits and properties of a bacterial cell",
      "the genes of all the species in a population"
    ],
    "correct": "the gene of a bacterial cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "A genotype (choose one wrong statement) :",
    "options": [
      "includes the nucleotide sequences of mitochondrial DNA",
      "is the total number  of all the genes in a bacterial cell",
      "provides  phenotypical variability within normal limits",
      "participates in the realization of genetic information depending on environmental conditions",
      "is passed to daughter cells"
    ],
    "correct": "includes the nucleotide sequences of mitochondrial DNA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Phenotype is the total number of :",
    "options": [
      "all the traits and properties of a bacterial cell",
      "the genes of a bacterial cell",
      "the genes of all the species in a population",
      "the genes of a bacterial cell and plasmids"
    ],
    "correct": "all the traits and properties of a bacterial cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "Phenotype :",
    "options": [
      "is the total number of all  the traits and properties of a bacterial cell",
      "is the total number of the genes of a bacterial cell",
      "changes in strict correspondence with the change of the  genotype",
      "is inherited",
      "realizes all the genetic opportunities of a cell"
    ],
    "correct": "is the total number of all  the traits and properties of a bacterial cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "A mutation is:",
    "options": [
      "a change of a nucleotide sequence in DNA",
      "the transfer of isolated DNA from a donor cell to a recipient cell",
      "the transfer of a DNA segment from cell to cell with  the help of a bacteriophage",
      "the transfer of plasmids",
      "the repair of damaged genetic material"
    ],
    "correct": "a change of a nucleotide sequence in DNA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mutations are :",
    "options": [
      "a stable hereditary change of a trait",
      "the transfer of genetic material with the help of a bacteriophage",
      "the repair of damaged DNA segments"
    ],
    "correct": "a stable hereditary change of a trait"
  },
  {
    "question": "Recombination  is:",
    "options": [
      "the production  of bacterial  offspring  which has the traits of both a donor and a recipient",
      "the transfer of genetic material with the help of a bacteriophage",
      "the repair of damaged DNA segments",
      "a stable hereditary change of a trait"
    ],
    "correct": "the production  of bacterial  offspring  which has the traits of both a donor and a recipient"
  },
  {
    "question": "Conjugation  is:",
    "options": [
      "the exchange  of genetic  material  between  the bacterial cells of different gender",
      "the repair of damaged DNA",
      "the transfer of genetic material with the help of highly polymerized DNA",
      "the transfer of genetic material with the help of temperate  bacteriophages"
    ],
    "correct": "the exchange  of genetic  material  between  the bacterial cells of different gender"
  },
  {
    "question": "Transduction is :",
    "options": [
      "the transfer of a DNA segment from one bacterial cell to another with the help of a bacteriophage",
      "the transfer of plasmids",
      "the transfer of genetic material with the help of F-pilli",
      "the determination  of the primary  sequence of nucleic acids"
    ],
    "correct": "the transfer of a DNA segment from one bacterial cell to another with the help of a bacteriophage"
  },
  {
    "question": "Transformation is :",
    "options": [
      "the transfer of genetic material with the help of highly polymerized DNA",
      "the exchange of genetic material between bacterial cells of different gender",
      "the repair of damaged DNA",
      "the transfer of genetic material with the help of temperate bacteriophages"
    ],
    "correct": "the transfer of genetic material with the help of highly polymerized DNA"
  },
  {
    "question": "The transfer of genetic information with the help of a phage is :",
    "options": [
      "transduction",
      "transformation",
      "viropexis",
      "lysogeny",
      "phage conversion"
    ],
    "correct": "transduction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Transposons :",
    "options": [
      "are mob ile genetic elements",
      "independent replicons which are extrachr omosomal inheritance factors",
      "participate in DNA repair",
      "participate in specific transduction"
    ],
    "correct": "are mob ile genetic elements"
  },
  {
    "question": "Transposons :",
    "options": [
      "are nucleotide  sequences",
      "are amino acid sequences",
      "are able to change their position  within only one replicon",
      "are able to replicate in an autonomous state"
    ],
    "correct": "are nucleotide  sequences"
  },
  {
    "question": "Plasmids :",
    "options": [
      "are independent replicons which are extrachromosomal inheritance factors",
      "participate in DNA repair",
      "participate  in specific transduction",
      "are mobile genetic elements"
    ],
    "correct": "are independent replicons which are extrachromosomal inheritance factors"
  },
  {
    "question": "A polymerase chain reaction (PCR) is:",
    "options": [
      "a multicycle process of DNA replication",
      "a bacterial genome sequencing",
      "a multicycle process of protein sequences",
      "used for bacterial phage typing",
      "measured by photocolorimetry"
    ],
    "correct": "a multicycle process of DNA replication"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is not true for a ntigens ?",
    "options": [
      "normal  microbiota  species are not antigens",
      "they are substances, cells",
      "they are genetically foreign",
      "they cause  the immune  response",
      "they interact with the products of the immune response"
    ],
    "correct": "normal  microbiota  species are not antigens"
  },
  {
    "question": "Antigens as substances are :",
    "options": [
      "proteins",
      "lipids",
      "polysaccharides",
      "nucleic acids",
      "salts"
    ],
    "correct": "proteins"
  },
  {
    "question": "Antigenicity is :",
    "options": [
      "capacity to stimulate antibodies production",
      "immunologic affinity",
      "capacity to cause an infectious disease",
      "the capacity of macrophages to participate in phagocytosis",
      "production of interferon"
    ],
    "correct": "capacity to stimulate antibodies production"
  },
  {
    "question": "Monotrichous microbes have :",
    "options": [
      "one flagellum at the pole of a cell",
      "a bundle of flagella at one pole",
      "flagella covering the whole surface",
      "flagella at both poles",
      "no flagella"
    ],
    "correct": "one flagellum at the pole of a cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lophotrichous microbes have :",
    "options": [
      "a bundle of flagella at one pole",
      "one flagellum at the pole of a cell",
      "flagella covering the whole surface",
      "flagella at both poles",
      "no flagella"
    ],
    "correct": "a bundle of flagella at one pole"
  },
  {
    "question": "Amphitrichous microbes have :",
    "options": [
      "flagella at both poles",
      "a bundle of flagella at one pole",
      "one flagellum at the pole of a cell",
      "flagella covering the whole surface",
      "no flagella"
    ],
    "correct": "flagella at both poles"
  },
  {
    "question": "Atrichous microbes have :",
    "options": [
      "no flagella",
      "flagella at both poles",
      "a bundle of flagella at one pole",
      "one flagellum at the pole of a cell",
      "flagella covering the whole surface"
    ],
    "correct": "no flagella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Peritrichous microbes have :",
    "options": [
      "flagella covering the whole surface",
      "no flagella",
      "flagella at both poles",
      "a bundle of flagella at one pole",
      "one flagellum at the pole of a cell"
    ],
    "correct": "flagella covering the whole surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacterial spores are :",
    "options": [
      "dormant reproductive cells",
      "intracellular inclusions",
      "a form of reproduction",
      "a virulence factor",
      "plasmids"
    ],
    "correct": "dormant reproductive cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Branching microorganisms include :",
    "options": [
      "actinomyces",
      "spirilla",
      "vibrions",
      "spirochetes",
      "bacilli"
    ],
    "correct": "actinomyces"
  },
  {
    "question": "Autotrophs  are the microbes  whose  source  of carbon is :",
    "options": [
      "only СО",
      "2",
      "polyphosphates",
      "lipids",
      "different organic compounds"
    ],
    "correct": "only СО"
  },
  {
    "question": "Phototrophs are the microbes whose source of energy is :",
    "options": [
      "solar energy",
      "redox reactions",
      "penetrating radiation",
      "X-rays",
      "electricity"
    ],
    "correct": "solar energy"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cultural properties of bacteria are :",
    "options": [
      "the speed and type of growth of cultures on growth media",
      "the morphology of bacteria",
      "capacity to take up stains",
      "type of metabolism",
      "type of respiration"
    ],
    "correct": "the speed and type of growth of cultures on growth media"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cultural properties of bacteria are :",
    "options": [
      "the morphology of colonies",
      "the morphology of bacteria",
      "capacity to cause a disease",
      "type of metabolism",
      "intensity of metabolism"
    ],
    "correct": "the morphology of colonies"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteriological  diagnosing  method  (the microbiological culture technique) is used to :",
    "options": [
      "isolate and identify the bacteria which are the causative agents of diseases",
      "detect antibodies in a patient’s blood serum",
      "detect antigens in the test material",
      "isolate and identify the viruses which are the causative agents of diseases"
    ],
    "correct": "isolate and identify the bacteria which are the causative agents of diseases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Normal microflora (microbiota) is an open microbiocoenosis of :",
    "options": [
      "the human body cavities which have a connection with the external environment",
      "all the body cavities of the human",
      "the body cavities which do not have a connection with the external environment",
      "anaerobic microorganisms which inhabit different biotopes",
      "potentially pathogenic (oppor tunistic) microorganisms which inhabit different biotopes"
    ],
    "correct": "the human body cavities which have a connection with the external environment"
  },
  {
    "question": "A biofilm is :",
    "options": [
      "a structured assemblage of microbes on the surface of mucous membranes",
      "the growth of isolate colonies",
      "the bacterial lawn growth on agar",
      "the growth of bacteria in broth",
      "secretory IgA on the surface of mucous membranes"
    ],
    "correct": "a structured assemblage of microbes on the surface of mucous membranes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most  correct  and complete  definition of dy sbiosis  (dysbacteriosis)  is:",
    "options": [
      "the changes  in the species  and number  of the biotope  normal  microbiota which are outside the physiological",
      "normal limits",
      "the decrease  in the number  of typical  coliform bacteria in a certain biotope in the body",
      "the increase  of the total number  of putrefying and spore -forming bacteria  in the biotope",
      "short -time changes in the microbiota of the intestine"
    ],
    "correct": "the changes  in the species  and number  of the biotope  normal  microbiota which are outside the physiological"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dysbiosis (dysbacteriosis) is :",
    "options": [
      "the changes  in the species  and number  of the human  normal  microbiota which are outside the physiological",
      "normal limits",
      "the disruption in the human normal microbiota",
      "the numerical disruption in the human normal microbiota",
      "the presence of pathogenic microbiota"
    ],
    "correct": "the changes  in the species  and number  of the human  normal  microbiota which are outside the physiological"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dysbiosis  (dysbacteriosis ) is:",
    "options": [
      "the disruption  in the number and species content of microbiota",
      "a hospital -acquired infection",
      "transmitted through contact",
      "an infectious  disease",
      "inherited"
    ],
    "correct": "the disruption  in the number and species content of microbiota"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dysbiosis (dysbacteriosis) :",
    "options": [
      "is always secondary",
      "is an infectious disease",
      "does not affect human health",
      "is always primary",
      "does not have any clinical manifestations"
    ],
    "correct": "is always secondary"
  },
  {
    "question": "The dysbiosis of the intestine is accompanied with all the following manifestations  except :",
    "options": [
      "the increase of colonization resistance",
      "the decrease in the number of bifidobacteria",
      "the presence of hemolyzing E.coli",
      "the presence of a great amount  of Candida  species yeast",
      "the increase  in the number  of potentially patho genic (opportunistic) microorganisms"
    ],
    "correct": "the increase of colonization resistance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteriophages are :",
    "options": [
      "obligatory bacterial parasites",
      "obligatory viral parasites",
      "prokaryotes",
      "eukaryotes",
      "infectious agents causing human diseases"
    ],
    "correct": "obligatory bacterial parasites"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteriophages are :",
    "options": [
      "the viruses of bacteria",
      "macrophages",
      "prokaryotes",
      "eukaryotes",
      "prions"
    ],
    "correct": "the viruses of bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Phage (lysogenic) conversion is :",
    "options": [
      "the change  in the properties  of bacteria  which occurs when bacteria acquire additional genetic information",
      "brought by the genome of a temperate phage",
      "a stage of the interaction between a virulent bacteriophage and a bacterial cell",
      "the transfer  of genes  from a donor cell to a recipient cell with the help of a virulent bacteriophage",
      "the transfer  of genes  from a donor cell to a recipient cell with the help of a temperate bacteriophage"
    ],
    "correct": "the change  in the properties  of bacteria  which occurs when bacteria acquire additional genetic information"
  },
  {
    "question": "The titer of a bacteriophage is :",
    "options": [
      "the maxim al dilution  of phage -containing material in which the complete lysis of sensitive culture is still",
      "observed",
      "the minimal  dilution  of phage -containing material in which the complete lysis of sensitive culture is still",
      "observed",
      "the maximal  dilution  of phage -containing material in which the complete lysis of sensitive culture is not"
    ],
    "correct": "the maxim al dilution  of phage -containing material in which the complete lysis of sensitive culture is still"
  },
  {
    "question": "A prophage is :",
    "options": [
      "the DNA of a temperate phage integrated into a bacterial chromosome",
      "the precursor of a phage particle at the stage of the phage offspring assembly",
      "the DNA of a virulent phage integrated into bacterial chromosome",
      "the DNA of a virulent bacteriophage",
      "a defective phage"
    ],
    "correct": "the DNA of a temperate phage integrated into a bacterial chromosome"
  },
  {
    "question": "Commensalism is a type of symbiosis during which:",
    "options": [
      "one organism lives benefiting from the other while not causing any harm to it",
      "one organism  continues  the process  caused  by the other  relieving it from metab olites",
      "the coexistence of microbes and a macroorganism which is beneficial for both",
      "one organism benefits from the other while causing harm to it",
      "the coexistence of two microorganisms which is beneficial for both"
    ],
    "correct": "one organism lives benefiting from the other while not causing any harm to it"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mutualism is:",
    "options": [
      "the coexistence of different organisms which is beneficial for both",
      "one organism  continues  the process  caused  by the other  relieving it from metabolites",
      "one organism lives benefiting from the other while not causing any harm to it",
      "the intensification  of physiological functions and properties of bacteria which occurs if t hey are cultured",
      "together"
    ],
    "correct": "the coexistence of different organisms which is beneficial for both"
  },
  {
    "question": "Microbiocoenosis is :",
    "options": [
      "a community of microorganisms’ populations which inhabit a certain biotope",
      "a place of a microbial population’s habitation",
      "the total number of the individuals of one species which inhabit a certain biotope",
      "the cooperative functioning different biocoenoses",
      "the coexistence of microbes and a microorganism beneficial for both"
    ],
    "correct": "a community of microorganisms’ populations which inhabit a certain biotope"
  },
  {
    "question": "Biotope is :",
    "options": [
      "a place of habit ation of a microbial population",
      "the total number of the individuals of one species which inhabit a certain biotope",
      "a community of microorganisms’ populations which inhabit a certain biotope",
      "the cooperative functioning different biocoenoses",
      "the total number of the individuals of one species which inhabit a certain biocoenosis"
    ],
    "correct": "a place of habit ation of a microbial population"
  },
  {
    "question": "An infectious process is :",
    "options": [
      "a process of penetration and multiplication of microbes in a microorganism accompanied by the damage done",
      "to the tissue and organs and the development of adaptive defense response",
      "a process of penetration of a microbe into an organism",
      "the inflammation caused by microbes or their toxins",
      "a process which occurs when microbes fill an ecological niche in an organism"
    ],
    "correct": "a process of penetration and multiplication of microbes in a microorganism accompanied by the damage done"
  },
  {
    "question": "is known as :",
    "options": [
      "pathogenicity",
      "antigenicity",
      "agressiveness",
      "toxigenicity",
      "adhesiveness"
    ],
    "correct": "pathogenicity"
  },
  {
    "question": "A recurrence  of an endogenous infection is  known as a :",
    "options": [
      "relapse (recidivism)",
      "superinfection",
      "reinfection",
      "mixed infection",
      "autoinfection"
    ],
    "correct": "relapse (recidivism)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A reinfection :",
    "options": [
      "is a subsequent  infection  caused  by the same  microbe  after a complete recovery",
      "the appearance  of the manifestations  of the same disease after a seeming recovery caused by the pathogen",
      "which have remained in the body",
      "occurs when a new infection process caused by another microbe joins the existing infectious process",
      "an infectious disease caused by one pathogenic species"
    ],
    "correct": "is a subsequent  infection  caused  by the same  microbe  after a complete recovery"
  },
  {
    "question": "The infections  caused  during  medical  procedures  are known as :",
    "options": [
      "iatrogenic",
      "anthroponotic",
      "superinfections",
      "opportunistic",
      "focal infections"
    ],
    "correct": "iatrogenic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bactere mia occurs when :",
    "options": [
      "a pathogen is present in blood but does not multiply in it",
      "blood becomes the place of habitation and multiplication of microbes",
      "distant purulent foci appear in the internal organs",
      "bacterial toxins get into blood",
      "a great number of bacteria and their toxins get into blood"
    ],
    "correct": "a pathogen is present in blood but does not multiply in it"
  },
  {
    "question": "Toxigenicity of microorganisms is the :",
    "options": [
      "capacity to produce exotoxins",
      "capacity to produce endotoxins",
      "capacity to produce bacteriocins",
      "capacity to produce beta -lactamase",
      "capacity to produce lipids"
    ],
    "correct": "capacity to produce exotoxins"
  },
  {
    "question": "DLm is a unit of measurement of :",
    "options": [
      "virulence of microbes",
      "infectivity",
      "toxigenicity",
      "immunogenicity"
    ],
    "correct": "virulence of microbes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Serotyping  is an/a :",
    "options": [
      "identification  of an unknown  culture  of a microorganism with the help of a known diagnostic serum",
      "detection  of specific  antibodies in a patient’s blood serum with the help of a known antigen",
      "determination  of a microorganism ’s serotype with the help of a known antigenic diagnosticum",
      "detection of unknown antibodies in a patient’s blood serum with the help of an erythrocyte antigenic",
      "diagnosticum"
    ],
    "correct": "identification  of an unknown  culture  of a microorganism with the help of a known diagnostic serum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Serodiagnostic assay is :",
    "options": [
      "detetion of unknown antibodies in a patient’s blood serum with the help of a known antigenic diagnosticum",
      "detection  of specific antibodies in a patient’s blood serum with the help of a known monospecific serum",
      "identification of the microbial species isolated from a patient",
      "diagnosis of an infectious disease with the detection of microbial antigens in a patient’s blood serum",
      "identification of a serotype of a microorganism with the help of a known monospecific serum"
    ],
    "correct": "detetion of unknown antibodies in a patient’s blood serum with the help of a known antigenic diagnosticum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tinctorial properties of bac teria are :",
    "options": [
      "the capacity to retain stains",
      "the resistance to environmental and chemical factors",
      "the belonging to a particular genus or species",
      "antibiotic sensitivity",
      "sensitivity to bacteriophages"
    ],
    "correct": "the capacity to retain stains"
  },
  {
    "question": "Antigens of microorganisms can be everything except :",
    "options": [
      "isoantigenic",
      "somatic",
      "capsule",
      "flagellar",
      "toxins"
    ],
    "correct": "isoantigenic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Н-antigen of bacteria is located in the :",
    "options": [
      "flagella",
      "cell wall",
      "capsule",
      "outer membrane"
    ],
    "correct": "flagella"
  },
  {
    "question": "К-antigen of bacteria is located in the :",
    "options": [
      "capsule",
      "cell wall",
      "outer membrane",
      "flagella"
    ],
    "correct": "capsule"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vi-antigen of bacteria is located in :",
    "options": [
      "capsule",
      "cell wall",
      "outer membrane",
      "flagella"
    ],
    "correct": "capsule"
  },
  {
    "question": "О-antigen of gram -negative bacteria is located in :",
    "options": [
      "outer membrane",
      "mesosomes",
      "capsule",
      "flagella"
    ],
    "correct": "outer membrane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Immunobiological preparations include everything except :",
    "options": [
      "antibiotics",
      "vaccines",
      "immune sera",
      "immunoglobulin preparations",
      "immunomodulators"
    ],
    "correct": "antibiotics"
  },
  {
    "question": "The national vaccination schedule includes a compulsory vaccine against :",
    "options": [
      "diphtheria",
      "leptospirosis",
      "typhoid fever",
      "haemophilus influenzae infections",
      "rabies"
    ],
    "correct": "diphtheria"
  },
  {
    "question": "The national vaccination schedule includes a compulsory vaccine against :",
    "options": [
      "tetanus",
      "meningococcal infection",
      "yellow fever",
      "plague",
      "hepatitis A"
    ],
    "correct": "tetanus"
  },
  {
    "question": "The national vaccination schedule includes a compulsory vaccine against :",
    "options": [
      "hepatitis B",
      "tick-borne encephalitis",
      "cholera",
      "herpes viruses",
      "brucellosis"
    ],
    "correct": "hepatitis B"
  },
  {
    "question": "The national vaccination schedule includes a compulsory vaccine against :",
    "options": [
      "pertussis",
      "plague",
      "tularemia",
      "Pseudomonas aeruginosa",
      "hepatitis C"
    ],
    "correct": "pertussis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The national vaccination schedule includes a compulsory vaccine against :",
    "options": [
      "measles",
      "haemophilus influenzae infection",
      "meningococcal infection",
      "salmonella inf ection",
      "dysentery"
    ],
    "correct": "measles"
  },
  {
    "question": "The national vaccination schedule includes a compulsory vaccine against :",
    "options": [
      "mumps",
      "brucellosis",
      "smallpox",
      "chickenpox",
      "yersiniosis"
    ],
    "correct": "mumps"
  },
  {
    "question": "The national vaccination schedule includes a compulsory vaccine against everything except :",
    "options": [
      "rotavirus infection",
      "tetanus",
      "diphtheria",
      "tuberculosis",
      "rubella"
    ],
    "correct": "rotavirus infection"
  },
  {
    "question": "The infectious  diseases that can be prevented by vaccines in Russia are all the following except :",
    "options": [
      "salmonella  infection",
      "diphtheria",
      "pertussis",
      "measles",
      "polyomyelitis"
    ],
    "correct": "salmonella  infection"
  },
  {
    "question": "A live attenuated  vaccine  is used to prevent :",
    "options": [
      "tuberculossis",
      "botulism",
      "tetanus",
      "cholera",
      "diphtheria"
    ],
    "correct": "tuberculossis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which preparation is used for the pre -exposure (scheduled) prophylaxis (prevention) of diphtheria :",
    "options": [
      "DPT vaccine",
      "BCG vaccine",
      "diphtheria antitoxin serum",
      "diphtheria exotoxin",
      "a cephalosporin antibiotic"
    ],
    "correct": "DPT vaccine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which vaccine is used for the specific pre -exposure (scheduled) prevention of hepatitis B :",
    "options": [
      "genetically engineered",
      "live",
      "inactivated",
      "subunit",
      "adsorbed"
    ],
    "correct": "genetically engineered"
  },
  {
    "question": "The immunity which is produced by DPT vaccine is :",
    "options": [
      "antitoxic (to diphtheria and tetanus) and antimicrobi al (to pertussis)",
      "antimicrobial (to tetanus and diphtheria)",
      "antitoxic and antimicrobial (to diphtheria and tetanus)",
      "antitoxic  (to pertussis) and antimicrobial (to diphtheria and tetanus)",
      "antitoxic (to pertussis and tetanus)"
    ],
    "correct": "antitoxic (to diphtheria and tetanus) and antimicrobi al (to pertussis)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which vaccine is multivalent?",
    "options": [
      "DPT",
      "BCG",
      "plague  vaccine",
      "mumps  vaccine",
      "According  to the Russian  vaccination schedule newborns should be vaccinated in the first 24 hours of their life"
    ],
    "correct": "DPT"
  },
  {
    "question": "against :",
    "options": [
      "hepatitis B",
      "tuberculosis",
      "pertussis",
      "diphtheria",
      "tetanus"
    ],
    "correct": "hepatitis B"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccines can be of all these types except :",
    "options": [
      "semi -synthetic",
      "live (attenuated)",
      "killed (inactivated)",
      "toxoids (anatoxins)",
      "genetically engineered"
    ],
    "correct": "semi -synthetic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccines contain :",
    "options": [
      "microorganisms",
      "microorganisms’ metabolic by -products",
      "immune complexes",
      "immunocompetent cells",
      "cytokines"
    ],
    "correct": "microorganisms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccines contain everything except :",
    "options": [
      "live pathogenic microorganisms",
      "killed pathogenic microorganisms",
      "live attenuated strains of microorganisms",
      "inactivated toxins of microorganisms",
      "protective antigens"
    ],
    "correct": "live pathogenic microorganisms"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do vaccines cause to produce in the human body?",
    "options": [
      "active immunity",
      "post-serum im munity",
      "passive immunity",
      "species immunity",
      "tolerance state"
    ],
    "correct": "active immunity"
  },
  {
    "question": "The immunity which is produced by vaccines is :",
    "options": [
      "active artificially acquired",
      "innate",
      "active naturally acquired",
      "passive naturally acquired",
      "passive artificially acquired"
    ],
    "correct": "active artificially acquired"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccines should comply with all these requirements except :",
    "options": [
      "tolerogenicity",
      "high immunogenicity",
      "they should be harmless",
      "they should not be reactogenic",
      "minimal sensitization"
    ],
    "correct": "tolerogenicity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Live vaccines contain the strains of microorganisms :",
    "options": [
      "with a decreased virulence",
      "with an initial virulence",
      "with changed antigenic properties",
      "with an increased virulence",
      "inactivated by UV -rays"
    ],
    "correct": "with a decreased virulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "The advantage of live vaccine is :",
    "options": [
      "high immunity level",
      "high reactogenicity",
      "the immunity is formed straight after the vaccination",
      "they provide a life-long immunity",
      "they are easy to produce"
    ],
    "correct": "high immunity level"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which groups of people are forbidden to receive live vaccines?",
    "options": [
      "people with  both primary and acquired immunodeficiencies",
      "newborns",
      "teenagers",
      "people  with chronic  diseases",
      "people over  50 and older"
    ],
    "correct": "people with  both primary and acquired immunodeficiencies"
  },
  {
    "question": "Live vaccines have all these properties except :",
    "options": [
      "a life -long immunity",
      "high immunogenicity",
      "residual virulence",
      "the capacity to multiply in the human body",
      "the absence of prominent adverse reactions"
    ],
    "correct": "a life -long immunity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Chemical vaccines :",
    "options": [
      "contain protective antigens",
      "contain who le microbial cells",
      "contain hapte ns",
      "possess an immunosuppressive effect",
      "are administered only once"
    ],
    "correct": "contain protective antigens"
  },
  {
    "question": "The vaccine  which is used for the specific prevention of measles is :",
    "options": [
      "live",
      "genetically engineered",
      "killed",
      "chemical",
      "adsorbed"
    ],
    "correct": "live"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does not belong to corpuscular vaccines?",
    "options": [
      "toxoids (anatoxins )",
      "subcellular  vaccines",
      "subvirion  cells",
      "whole cell vaccines"
    ],
    "correct": "toxoids (anatoxins )"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of live vaccines which are produced with the use of weakened strains of microorganisms?",
    "options": [
      "attenuated",
      "divergent",
      "vector",
      "recombinant",
      "molecular"
    ],
    "correct": "attenuated"
  },
  {
    "question": "The production of the attenuated strains of microorganisms includes everything except :",
    "options": [
      "selecting high -virulence strains",
      "selectiong low -virulence strains",
      "culturing in unfavorable conditions",
      "serial passage by infecting resistant animals"
    ],
    "correct": "selecting high -virulence strains"
  },
  {
    "question": "The production of live attenuated vaccines involves :",
    "options": [
      "the decrease of the virulence of microorganisms while  culturing them in unfavorable conditions",
      "the treatment  of exotoxins with 0. 4 % formalin solution",
      "the extraction of protective antigens from a microbial  cell",
      "the inactivation of highly immunogenic strains of microorganisms though heating or chemical treatment",
      "chemical synthesis"
    ],
    "correct": "the decrease of the virulence of microorganisms while  culturing them in unfavorable conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "into the genome of other microorganisms which start synthesizing a corresponding antigen :",
    "options": [
      "genetically engineered",
      "chemical",
      "anti-idiotypic",
      "attenuated",
      "inactivated"
    ],
    "correct": "genetically engineered"
  },
  {
    "question": "Vaccines with an adjuvant are known as :",
    "options": [
      "adsorbed",
      "recombinant vector",
      "inactivated",
      "toxoids (anatoxins)",
      "live attenuated"
    ],
    "correct": "adsorbed"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect produced by adjuvants on the immune system?",
    "options": [
      "non-specific activation",
      "non-specific suppression",
      "specific suppression",
      "specific activation"
    ],
    "correct": "non-specific activation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Chemical vaccines are produced :",
    "options": [
      "from protective antigens extracted from a microbial cell",
      "by the transfer of the genes controlling necessary antigenic determinants into the genome of other",
      "microorganisms which start synthesizing a corresponding antigen",
      "from the strains of highly immunogenic microorganism which are inactivated with physical methods",
      "with the use of anti -idiotypic antibodies"
    ],
    "correct": "from protective antigens extracted from a microbial cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "Killed vaccines are produced :",
    "options": [
      "from the strains of highly immunogenic microorganism which are inactivated with physical and chemical",
      "methods",
      "the treatment  of exotoxins with 0. 4 % formalin solutio n",
      "with the use of anti -idiotypic antibodies",
      "by the decrease  of the virulence  of microorganisms while culturing them in unfavorable conditions"
    ],
    "correct": "from the strains of highly immunogenic microorganism which are inactivated with physical and chemical"
  },
  {
    "question": "The production of diagnostic agglutinating sera involves :",
    "options": [
      "hyperimmunization of laboratory animals with a corresponding antigen",
      "vaccination of a healthy person",
      "an agglutination reaction",
      "non-specific desensitization of the organism",
      "it is taken from sick people"
    ],
    "correct": "hyperimmunization of laboratory animals with a corresponding antigen"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the aim of using antigenic diagnosticums?",
    "options": [
      "to detect specific antibodies",
      "to determine a serotype",
      "to detect precipitinogen",
      "to produce a hemolytic serum"
    ],
    "correct": "to detect specific antibodies"
  },
  {
    "question": "Antitoxic immunity is provided by :",
    "options": [
      "immunization with a toxoid (anatoxin)",
      "injection of an endotoxin",
      "application of an antimicrobial serum",
      "immunization with any protein",
      "using subunit viral vaccines"
    ],
    "correct": "immunization with a toxoid (anatoxin)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is used for the serotherapy of infectious diseases?",
    "options": [
      "immune sera",
      "toxoids (anatoxins)",
      "chemical drugs",
      "vaccines",
      "antibiotics"
    ],
    "correct": "immune sera"
  },
  {
    "question": "Immune sera and immunoglobulins contain :",
    "options": [
      "specific antibodies",
      "vaccine strains",
      "killed microorganisms",
      "adjuvants",
      "toxoids (anatoxins)"
    ],
    "correct": "specific antibodies"
  },
  {
    "question": "Immune sera and immunoglobulins are used in case of infectious diseases for :",
    "options": [
      "seroprophylaxis, serotherapy",
      "serotherapy, vaccine therapy",
      "vaccine therapy, vaccine prophylaxis",
      "vaccine  prophylaxis , serotherapy",
      "seroprophylaxis , vaccine  therapy"
    ],
    "correct": "seroprophylaxis, serotherapy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Homologous immune sera are produced :",
    "options": [
      "from vaccinated people, from donated and placental blood",
      "by the hyperimmunization of horses with a corresponding toxoid (anatoxin)",
      "with the use of antiidiotypic antibodies",
      "by the trea tment of exotoxins with 0.4 % formalin solution",
      "by hyperimmunization of rabbits with a corresponding antigen"
    ],
    "correct": "from vaccinated people, from donated and placental blood"
  },
  {
    "question": "Heterologous sera and immunoglobulins are produced :",
    "options": [
      "by hyperimmunization of horses",
      "from donors’ blood",
      "from abortion blood",
      "from placental blood",
      "by the attenuation method"
    ],
    "correct": "by hyperimmunization of horses"
  },
  {
    "question": "Toxoids (anatoxins) contain :",
    "options": [
      "inactivated bacterial exotoxins",
      "a somatic antigen",
      "inactivated bacterial endotoxins",
      "bacterial exotoxins",
      "antitoxins"
    ],
    "correct": "inactivated bacterial exotoxins"
  },
  {
    "question": "The immunity  produced by a  diphtheria  toxoid is :",
    "options": [
      "antitoxic",
      "antibacterial",
      "anti-idiotypic",
      "antiviral",
      "mixed"
    ],
    "correct": "antitoxic"
  },
  {
    "question": "The production of antitoxic sera involves :",
    "options": [
      "the hyperimmunization of horses with a corresponding toxoid (anatoxin)",
      "the treatment of exotoxins with 0.4 % formalin solution",
      "the use of antiidiotypic antibodies",
      "hyperimmunization of rabbits with a corresponding antigen",
      "serial passage by infecting resistant animals"
    ],
    "correct": "the hyperimmunization of horses with a corresponding toxoid (anatoxin)"
  },
  {
    "question": "To produce an antitoxic serum laboratory animals are immunized with :",
    "options": [
      "a toxoid (anatoxin)",
      "the suspended matter of 24 hour bacterial  culture",
      "antitoxins",
      "an exotoxin",
      "antibodies"
    ],
    "correct": "a toxoid (anatoxin)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Immune sera are used for :",
    "options": [
      "immunotherapy  and post-exposure (urgent) immunoprophylaxis",
      "pre-exposure  (scheduled ) immunoprophylaxis",
      "producing an artificial active immunity",
      "vaccination and revaccination",
      "producing  a natural  immunity"
    ],
    "correct": "immunotherapy  and post-exposure (urgent) immunoprophylaxis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The criterion  for the evaluation  of serological tests with paired sera from a patient is :",
    "options": [
      "the increase of the antibody titer",
      "the norm of controls",
      "avidity of antibodies",
      "the time of collecting the serum",
      "the diagnostic  titer"
    ],
    "correct": "the increase of the antibody titer"
  },
  {
    "question": "The duration of the immunity produced by sera and immunoglobulins depends on :",
    "options": [
      "the half -life of  Ig",
      "the spectrum of activity of the drug",
      "the manufacturer",
      "the body reactivity",
      "a patient’s age"
    ],
    "correct": "the half -life of  Ig"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to their composition antibodies are :",
    "options": [
      "glycoproteins",
      "lipopolysaccharides",
      "nucleoprotein s",
      "gamma -globulins",
      "albumins"
    ],
    "correct": "glycoproteins"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a serum is administered intravenously the effect of the drug begins :",
    "options": [
      "immediately",
      "in 12 hours",
      "in 48 hours",
      "in 10 days",
      "starting from the 3-rd week"
    ],
    "correct": "immediately"
  },
  {
    "question": "The properties of bacteria studied with the help of microscopy are :",
    "options": [
      "morphological and tinctorial",
      "cultural",
      "antigenic",
      "toxigenic",
      "biochemical"
    ],
    "correct": "morphological and tinctorial"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aim of bacterioscopy is :",
    "options": [
      "to examine the morphology of microorganisms",
      "to produce the pure culture of microorganisms",
      "to create the model of an infectious process",
      "to detect microbial antigens",
      "to detect the DNA of a pathogen in a biological sample"
    ],
    "correct": "to examine the morphology of microorganisms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  properties  of bacteria is studied with the help of microscopy are :",
    "options": [
      "morphological",
      "cultural",
      "antigenic",
      "biochemical",
      "antibiotic sensitivity"
    ],
    "correct": "morphological"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  is not a kind of optical microscopy?",
    "options": [
      "electron microscopy",
      "phase -contrast microscopy",
      "dark-field microscopy",
      "oil immersion microscopy"
    ],
    "correct": "electron microscopy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of microscopy is used to study the motility of bacteria by the hanging drop method?",
    "options": [
      "dark-field",
      "fluorescent",
      "oil immersion",
      "electron"
    ],
    "correct": "dark-field"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  technique  is used to study the motility of microorganisms in a native sample?",
    "options": [
      "dark-field microscopy",
      "fuchsine staining",
      "fluorochrome treatment",
      "Loeffler stain",
      "Morozov silver stain"
    ],
    "correct": "dark-field microscopy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of microscopy is used to examine the ultrastructure of bac teria and viruses?",
    "options": [
      "electron",
      "fluorescent",
      "dark-field",
      "phase -contrast",
      "oil immersion"
    ],
    "correct": "electron"
  },
  {
    "question": "Native non -stained samples are prepared for this type of microscopy :",
    "options": [
      "phase contrast",
      "optical",
      "fluorescent",
      "electron",
      "oil immersion"
    ],
    "correct": "phase contrast"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of microscopy is used to detect  the antigens of microorganisms with the help of labeled antibodies?",
    "options": [
      "fluorescent",
      "phase contrast",
      "optical",
      "electron",
      "oil immersion"
    ],
    "correct": "fluorescent"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  type of sample  is prepared  to determine  the motility  of living  bacteria ?",
    "options": [
      "a “squashed drop” sample",
      "an impression smear",
      "twin smears",
      "a Burri smear"
    ],
    "correct": "a “squashed drop” sample"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dark -field microscopy is based on :",
    "options": [
      "the diffraction  of light while the object is illuminated from the side",
      "the fluorescence  of an object  in the visible spectrum",
      "the interference of  light waves",
      "the absorption of light by an object",
      "the transmission of light by an object"
    ],
    "correct": "the diffraction  of light while the object is illuminated from the side"
  },
  {
    "question": "Fluorescent microscopy is based on :",
    "options": [
      "the capacity  of some  substances  to emit light under the influence of short -wave length  radiation",
      "the decrease  of the intensity of object illumination by means of lowering the condenser and narrowing the",
      "diaphragm",
      "the conversion  of phase  oscillations  into amplitude oscillations by optical devices",
      "the submersion  of an immersion  objective  lens into immersion oil to prevent additional diffraction of a light"
    ],
    "correct": "the capacity  of some  substances  to emit light under the influence of short -wave length  radiation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What  is not  the advantage of microscopy as a method of infectious diseases diagnosis?",
    "options": [
      "the determination of virulence",
      "the possibility of rapid testing",
      "simplicity and availability",
      "it can have an independent di agnostic significance",
      "it helps to determine a clinically significant quantity of potentially pathogenic microorganisms"
    ],
    "correct": "the determination of virulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "The advantage of the immersion system is :",
    "options": [
      "the increase of the resolving power of an optical microscope",
      "a 3D image of an object",
      "a higher magnification of the objective lens",
      "a higher magnification of the eyepiece",
      "the use of UV -rays"
    ],
    "correct": "the increase of the resolving power of an optical microscope"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which procedure is compulsory before the staining of a sample?",
    "options": [
      "the fixation of a sample",
      "treating a sample with a developer",
      "drying a sample",
      "rinsing a sa mple with water",
      "treating a sample with immersion oil"
    ],
    "correct": "the fixation of a sample"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aniline dyes include all the ones mentioned below except:",
    "options": [
      "Lugol’s iodine",
      "fuchsine",
      "methylene blue",
      "crystal violet",
      "neutral red"
    ],
    "correct": "Lugol’s iodine"
  },
  {
    "question": "The method to detect chlamydia is :",
    "options": [
      "Giemsa stain ing",
      "Zdrodovsky staining",
      "Gram staining",
      "methylene blue staining",
      "Morozov silver staining"
    ],
    "correct": "Giemsa stain ing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Acid -fast bacteria are :",
    "options": [
      "mycobacteria",
      "mycoplasma",
      "streptococci",
      "Pseudomonas aeruginosa",
      "meningococci"
    ],
    "correct": "mycobacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "What  is the correct  order  of using the reagents in  Ziehl -Neelsen  staining  technique?",
    "options": [
      "carbol fuchsine, sulfuric acid, methylene blue",
      "methylene blue, carbol fuchsine, sulfuric acid",
      "sulfuric acid, carbol fuchsine, methylene blue",
      "carbol fuchsine, methylene blue, sulfuric acid",
      "methylene  blue, sulfuric acid, carbol fuchsine"
    ],
    "correct": "carbol fuchsine, sulfuric acid, methylene blue"
  },
  {
    "question": "What  is the correct  order  of the basic stages in  Aujeszky ’s staining  technique?",
    "options": [
      "hydrochloric acid, heating until vapor appears, fixation of a sample, Ziehl -Neelsen staining",
      "fixation  of a sample , Neisser staining , heating until vapor appears , hydrochloric  acid",
      "fixation  of a sample , hydrochloric  acid, heating until vapor appears , Neisser staining",
      "fixation  of a sample , hydrochloric  acid, heating until vapor appears , Ziehl -Neelsen staining",
      "hydrochloric  acid, fixation  of a sample , Lugol’s iodine staining , heating until vapor appears"
    ],
    "correct": "hydrochloric acid, heating until vapor appears, fixation of a sample, Ziehl -Neelsen staining"
  },
  {
    "question": "What  is the correct  order  of using the reagents in  Burri -Gins  staining  technique?",
    "options": [
      "a drop of India ink , fixation  of a sample  with alcohol , heating , Pfeiffer fuchsine",
      "fixation  of a sample  with alcohol , heating , a drop of India ink , Pfeiffer fuchsine",
      "fixation  of a sample  with alcohol , a drop of India ink , heating , methylene blue",
      "a drop of India ink , heating , fixation  of a sample  with alcohol , methylene blue",
      "fixation  of a sample  with alcohol , heating , basic fuchsine , a drop of India ink"
    ],
    "correct": "a drop of India ink , fixation  of a sample  with alcohol , heating , Pfeiffer fuchsine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  dyes are used in Giemsa  staining  technique?",
    "options": [
      "methylene  blue, azure , eosin",
      "crystal violet , azure  and methylene  blue",
      "crystal violet , eosin  and basic fuchsine",
      "methylene  blue and vesuvine",
      "methylene  blue, azure  and basic fuchsine"
    ],
    "correct": "methylene  blue, azure , eosin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which staining technique is used to detect inclusions in bacteria :",
    "options": [
      "Neisser stain",
      "Aujeszky stain",
      "Giemsa stain",
      "Burri -Gins stain",
      "Zdrodovsky stain"
    ],
    "correct": "Neisser stain"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dark -field microscopy is used to examine :",
    "options": [
      "Treponema  pallidum",
      "E.coli",
      "staphylococci",
      "chlamydia",
      "rickettsia"
    ],
    "correct": "Treponema  pallidum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Phase -contrast  microscopy  is used to examine :",
    "options": [
      "mycoplasma",
      "E.coli",
      "staphylococci",
      "pneumococci",
      "mycobacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "mycoplasma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Giemsa stain is used to detect :",
    "options": [
      "borrelia",
      "actinomyces",
      "mycoplasma",
      "staphylococci",
      "clostridia"
    ],
    "correct": "borrelia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Zdrodovsky stain is used to detect :",
    "options": [
      "rickettsia",
      "corynebacteria",
      "gonococci",
      "Vibrio  cholerae",
      "pneumococci"
    ],
    "correct": "rickettsia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ziehl -Neelsen stain is used to detect :",
    "options": [
      "mycobacteria",
      "shigella",
      "actinomyces",
      "corynebacteria",
      "clostridia"
    ],
    "correct": "mycobacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Neisser stain is used to detect :",
    "options": [
      "corynebacteria",
      "mycobacteria",
      "salmonella",
      "borrelia",
      "streptococci"
    ],
    "correct": "corynebacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Morozov silver stain is used to detect :",
    "options": [
      "treponema",
      "Vibrio cholerae",
      "chlamydia",
      "mycoplasma",
      "fungi"
    ],
    "correct": "treponema"
  },
  {
    "question": "The morphology of bacteria depends on :",
    "options": [
      "the structure of the cell wall",
      "the consistency of the growth medium",
      "the composition of the growth medium",
      "the stains which are used",
      "the fixation technique"
    ],
    "correct": "the structure of the cell wall"
  },
  {
    "question": "If we know the structure of bacteria we can do all the things mentioned below except :",
    "options": [
      "evaluate the immune status of a macroorganism",
      "identify bacteria",
      "produce vaccines",
      "study pathogenicity factors",
      "develop disinfection and sterilization techniques"
    ],
    "correct": "evaluate the immune status of a macroorganism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  bacterial  structures  are not  the targets for antimicrobial drugs?",
    "options": [
      "capsules",
      "the cell wall",
      "the plasma membrane",
      "ribosomes"
    ],
    "correct": "capsules"
  },
  {
    "question": "The obligate organelles of a prokaryotic cell are all the ones mentioned below except :",
    "options": [
      "plasmids",
      "mesosomes",
      "the nucleoid",
      "the cell wall",
      "ribosomes"
    ],
    "correct": "plasmids"
  },
  {
    "question": "The detection of these structures is significant for a differential diagnosis :",
    "options": [
      "spores",
      "the nucleoid",
      "the plasma membrane",
      "ribosomes",
      "mesosomes"
    ],
    "correct": "spores"
  },
  {
    "question": "Spore -forming bacteria are :",
    "options": [
      "bacilli",
      "spirilla",
      "cocci",
      "enterobacteria",
      "chlamydia"
    ],
    "correct": "bacilli"
  },
  {
    "question": "Spore -forming bacteria are :",
    "options": [
      "clostridia",
      "spirochetes",
      "coccobacteria",
      "sarcinae",
      "rickettsia"
    ],
    "correct": "clostridia"
  },
  {
    "question": "For some prokaryotes the formation of spores is :",
    "options": [
      "the way they react to any harmful effect produced on the cell",
      "the way of reproduction",
      "the accumulation of certain nutr ients",
      "an obligatory stage of the microbial life cycle",
      "the protection of the cell from phagocytosis"
    ],
    "correct": "the way they react to any harmful effect produced on the cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which structure of a bacterial cell if facultative?",
    "options": [
      "a flagellum",
      "the plasma membrane",
      "nucleoid",
      "ribosomes"
    ],
    "correct": "a flagellum"
  },
  {
    "question": "What  belongs  to the additional structures of bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "villi",
      "the periplasm",
      "the plasma membrane",
      "the nucleoid"
    ],
    "correct": "villi"
  },
  {
    "question": "What belongs to the surface structures of bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "capsules",
      "the cell wall",
      "the plasma membrane",
      "the periplasm",
      "plasmids"
    ],
    "correct": "capsules"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which structures belong to intracellular inclusions of bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "glycogen granules",
      "mitochondria",
      "ribosomes",
      "plasmids",
      "nucleoli"
    ],
    "correct": "glycogen granules"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which structures belong to intracellular inclusions of bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "volutin  granules",
      "contractile vacuoles",
      "ribosomes",
      "the nucleoid",
      "mesosomes"
    ],
    "correct": "volutin  granules"
  },
  {
    "question": "The presence  of volutin  granules is a diagnostic characteristic of :",
    "options": [
      "Corynebacterium diphtheriae",
      "E.coli",
      "clostridia",
      "botulism",
      "Bacillus anthracis"
    ],
    "correct": "Corynebacterium diphtheriae"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microbes do not have a cell wall?",
    "options": [
      "mycoplasma",
      "actinomyces",
      "spirochetes",
      "chlamydia",
      "rickettsia"
    ],
    "correct": "mycoplasma"
  },
  {
    "question": "The rigidity  of the cell wall is provided by :",
    "options": [
      "peptidoglycan",
      "proteins",
      "teichoic acids",
      "lipopolysaccharides",
      "phospholipids"
    ],
    "correct": "peptidoglycan"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacterial cell wall possesses all the properties mentioned below except :",
    "options": [
      "it participates in protein synthesis",
      "it contains the basic antigens of a microbial cell",
      "it determines the shape of a bacterium",
      "it protects from environmental effects",
      "it can determine the result of Gram staining"
    ],
    "correct": "it participates in protein synthesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cell wall of gram -negative bacteria does not include :",
    "options": [
      "teichoic acids",
      "peptidoglycan",
      "proteins of the outer membrane",
      "lipopolysaccharide"
    ],
    "correct": "teichoic acids"
  },
  {
    "question": "The basic structural component of the cell wall in gram -negative bacteria is :",
    "options": [
      "lipopolysaccharides",
      "teichoic acids",
      "lipoteichoic acids",
      "mycolic  acids",
      "proteins"
    ],
    "correct": "lipopolysaccharides"
  },
  {
    "question": "The basic structural component of the cell wall in gram -positive bacteria is :",
    "options": [
      "peptidoglycan",
      "teichoic acids",
      "mycolic acids",
      "lipopolysaccharides",
      "lipids"
    ],
    "correct": "peptidoglycan"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is contained only in the cell wall of gram -positive bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "a teichoic acid",
      "lipopolysaccharide",
      "murein",
      "protein",
      "peptidoglycan"
    ],
    "correct": "a teichoic acid"
  },
  {
    "question": "The function of lipopolysaccharide  is :",
    "options": [
      "О-antigen",
      "enzymatic",
      "exotoxin",
      "messenger",
      "protein synthesis"
    ],
    "correct": "О-antigen"
  },
  {
    "question": "A property of lipopolysaccharide is :",
    "options": [
      "it is an endotoxin",
      "it is thermolabile",
      "it contains  peptidoglycan",
      "it is an exotoxin",
      "it stores the nutrients of a cell"
    ],
    "correct": "it is an endotoxin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is lipopolysaccharide located in a bacterial cell?",
    "options": [
      "in the outer membrane of gram -negative bacteria",
      "in the plasma  membrane",
      "in the outer membrane of gram -positive bacteria",
      "in mesosomes",
      "in the capsule"
    ],
    "correct": "in the outer membrane of gram -negative bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is contained in the cell wall of gram -positive bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "multilayered  peptidoglycan , teichoic and  lipoteichoic acids",
      "single -layered  peptidoglycan , lipopolysaccharide in the outer membrane",
      "a phospholipid bilayer , teichoic and lipo teichoic acids",
      "lipopolysaccharide in the outer membrane",
      "multilayered peptidoglycan , lipopolysaccharide in the outer membrane"
    ],
    "correct": "multilayered  peptidoglycan , teichoic and  lipoteichoic acids"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is contained in the cell wall of gram -negative bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "single -layered  peptidoglycan, lipopolysaccharide in the outer membrane",
      "multilayered  peptidoglycan, teichoic and  lipoteichoic acids",
      "single -layered  peptidoglycan, teichoic and  lipoteichoic acids",
      "single -layered  peptidoglycan  and cord factor",
      "a phospholipid bilayer , teichoic and lipo teichoic acids"
    ],
    "correct": "single -layered  peptidoglycan, lipopolysaccharide in the outer membrane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  structure  of the bacterial  cell wall enables bacteria to attach to the surface of cells?",
    "options": [
      "microvilli  (pili)",
      "spores",
      "flagella",
      "mesosomes",
      "О-antigen"
    ],
    "correct": "microvilli  (pili)"
  },
  {
    "question": "their original shape are known as :",
    "options": [
      "protoplasts",
      "spheroplasts",
      "mycoplasma",
      "mycobacteria",
      "stable  L-forms"
    ],
    "correct": "protoplasts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteria  which  retain  part of their cell wall and are able to restore their original shape are known as :",
    "options": [
      "spheroplasts",
      "protoplasts",
      "mycoplasma",
      "mycobacteria",
      "stable  L-forms"
    ],
    "correct": "spheroplasts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteria which have lost their capacity to synthesize peptidoglycan  but are able to reproduce are known as :",
    "options": [
      "L-form bacteria",
      "mycoplasma",
      "protoplasts",
      "spheroplasts",
      "chlamydia"
    ],
    "correct": "L-form bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "The absence of the cell wall is genetically predetermined in these microorganisms :",
    "options": [
      "mycoplasma",
      "protoplasts",
      "spheroplasts",
      "chlamydia",
      "L-form bacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "mycoplasma"
  },
  {
    "question": "L-form bacteria have a disruption in the synthesis of :",
    "options": [
      "the cell wall",
      "the capsule",
      "mesosomes",
      "the plasma membrane",
      "flagella"
    ],
    "correct": "the cell wall"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which process leads to the  L-form transformation of bacteria :",
    "options": [
      "the disruption of peptidoglycan  synthesis",
      "spore formation",
      "the conjugation of bacteria",
      "division",
      "a completed phagocytosis"
    ],
    "correct": "the disruption of peptidoglycan  synthesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "L-form bac teria have all the properties mentioned below except :",
    "options": [
      "they cause acute infections",
      "they cause chronic relapsing infections",
      "they are the form of the persistence of bacteria in the organism",
      "they are formed due to the inadequate treatment by chemotherapeutic  drugs",
      "they are gram -negative as a rule"
    ],
    "correct": "they cause acute infections"
  },
  {
    "question": "The shape of a bacterium is determined by the structure of its :",
    "options": [
      "cell wall",
      "plasma membrane",
      "murein",
      "spore",
      "capsule"
    ],
    "correct": "cell wall"
  },
  {
    "question": "living beings :",
    "options": [
      "it forms mesosomes",
      "it is three -layered",
      "it contains cholesterol",
      "it forms the endoplasmic reticulum"
    ],
    "correct": "it forms mesosomes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The p roteins  of the plasma membrane are subdivided into :",
    "options": [
      "transport and metabolic",
      "purines and pyrimidines",
      "basic and acidic",
      "complete and incomple te",
      "glycoproteins and chromoproteins"
    ],
    "correct": "transport and metabolic"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which structure carries bacterial antigens?",
    "options": [
      "flagella",
      "the plasma membrane",
      "mesosomes",
      "plasmids",
      "mitochondria"
    ],
    "correct": "flagella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which structure carries bacterial antigens?",
    "options": [
      "the capsule",
      "a spore",
      "the cytoplasm",
      "volutin granules",
      "cord factor"
    ],
    "correct": "the capsule"
  },
  {
    "question": "Unlike the cytoplasm of other living beings the bacterial cytoplasm does not contain :",
    "options": [
      "the endoplasmic reticulum",
      "inclusions",
      "ribosomes",
      "RNA",
      "DNA"
    ],
    "correct": "the endoplasmic reticulum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is genetic information located in a bacterial cell?",
    "options": [
      "in the nu cleoid",
      "in the plasma membrane",
      "in mesosomes",
      "in ribosomes",
      "in mitochondria"
    ],
    "correct": "in the nu cleoid"
  },
  {
    "question": "The function of the plasma membrane is :",
    "options": [
      "it participates in energy metabolism",
      "it determines the shape of bacteria",
      "it participates in the synthesis of biologically active substances",
      "drug resistance",
      "protection from phagocytosis"
    ],
    "correct": "it participates in energy metabolism"
  },
  {
    "question": "The function of ribosomes is :",
    "options": [
      "protein synthesis",
      "storage and realization of genetic information",
      "protection",
      "shape determination",
      "toxicity"
    ],
    "correct": "protein synthesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "A capsule is a distinguishing characteristic of :",
    "options": [
      "klebsiella",
      "streptococc i",
      "meningococci",
      "salmonella",
      "Vibrio cholerae"
    ],
    "correct": "klebsiella"
  },
  {
    "question": "A capsule is a distinguishing characteristic of :",
    "options": [
      "pneumococci",
      "gonococci",
      "staphylococci",
      "spirochetes",
      "shigella"
    ],
    "correct": "pneumococci"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is characteristic of the microcapsule?",
    "options": [
      "it is formed in the majority of bacteria",
      "it is visible through the optical microscope",
      "it makes bacteria acid -fast",
      "it is the framework of a bacterial cell",
      "it protects from the majority of antibiotics"
    ],
    "correct": "it is formed in the majority of bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the function of fimbriae (pili) in bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "the attachment to the substrate",
      "motility",
      "protection",
      "enzymatic"
    ],
    "correct": "the attachment to the substrate"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the function of fimbriae (pili) in bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "the exchange of genetic information",
      "sexual reproduction",
      "motility",
      "trophic"
    ],
    "correct": "the exchange of genetic information"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are the functions of bacterial fimbriae (pili) except :",
    "options": [
      "motility",
      "the attachment to the substrate",
      "the exchange of genetic information",
      "the participation in the water -salt metabolism"
    ],
    "correct": "motility"
  },
  {
    "question": "The organelles of motility in bacteria are :",
    "options": [
      "flagella",
      "pili",
      "pseudopods",
      "plasmids",
      "druses"
    ],
    "correct": "flagella"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacterial flagella :",
    "options": [
      "are made of flagellin protein",
      "participate in the transfer of genetic  material",
      "are typical mostly for gram -positive bacteria",
      "are obligate structure of a cell",
      "partici pate in spore formation"
    ],
    "correct": "are made of flagellin protein"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which ones are motile microorganisms?",
    "options": [
      "Escherichia coli",
      "staphylococci",
      "mycoplasma",
      "actinomyces",
      "streptococci"
    ],
    "correct": "Escherichia coli"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which structure enables a bacterial cell to persist in the environment for a long time?",
    "options": [
      "an endospore",
      "the cell wall",
      "the nucleoid",
      "the capsule",
      "a plasmid"
    ],
    "correct": "an endospore"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pathogenicity factor of bacteria is :",
    "options": [
      "the capsule",
      "a mesosome",
      "the nucleoid",
      "a spore",
      "inclusions"
    ],
    "correct": "the capsule"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pathogenicity factor of bacteria is :",
    "options": [
      "a flagellum",
      "the plasma membrane",
      "a plasmid",
      "a ribosome",
      "volutin granules"
    ],
    "correct": "a flagellum"
  },
  {
    "question": "The microorganisms reproducing with spores are :",
    "options": [
      "fungi",
      "chlamydia",
      "spirochetes",
      "protozoa",
      "viruses"
    ],
    "correct": "fungi"
  },
  {
    "question": "The function of bacterial endospores is :",
    "options": [
      "persistence (survival) in unfavorable conditions",
      "reproduction in favorable conditions",
      "protection from phagocytosis and antibodies",
      "prevention of the osmotic lysis of a cell",
      "adhesion  to susceptible  host cells"
    ],
    "correct": "persistence (survival) in unfavorable conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacterial e ndospores are :",
    "options": [
      "thermostable",
      "thermolabile",
      "sensitive to disinfectants",
      "used to control disinfection",
      "formed  in the host organism"
    ],
    "correct": "thermostable"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacterial endospores :",
    "options": [
      "are resistant to disinfectants",
      "are thermolabile",
      "are sensitive to antibiotics",
      "perform a reproductive function"
    ],
    "correct": "are resistant to disinfectants"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacterial endospores have all the properties mentioned below except :",
    "options": [
      "sensitivity to antibiotics",
      "thermostability",
      "resistance to disinfectants",
      "they are used to control the sterilization of the autoclave",
      "they are formed in unfavorable environmental conditions"
    ],
    "correct": "sensitivity to antibiotics"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microorganisms produce spores :",
    "options": [
      "clostridia",
      "enterobacteria",
      "staphylococci",
      "viruses",
      "vibrions"
    ],
    "correct": "clostridia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  bacteria  produce  spores  which are bigger than bacterial cells?",
    "options": [
      "clostridia",
      "mycoplasma",
      "bacilli",
      "spirochetes",
      "yersiniae"
    ],
    "correct": "clostridia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  bacteria  produce  spores  which are not bigger than bacterial cells?",
    "options": [
      "bacilli",
      "campylobacter",
      "clostridia",
      "spirochetes",
      "brucellae"
    ],
    "correct": "bacilli"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  phase  of the cell cycle  involves  spore  formation?",
    "options": [
      "stationary phase",
      "lag phase",
      "log phase (exponential)",
      "death phase"
    ],
    "correct": "stationary phase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which bacteria form a capsule while being cultured in artificial growth media?",
    "options": [
      "klebsiella",
      "pneumococci",
      "gonococci",
      "mycoplasma",
      "bacilli"
    ],
    "correct": "klebsiella"
  },
  {
    "question": "The function of the bacterial capsule is :",
    "options": [
      "antiphagocytic",
      "locomotive",
      "reproductive",
      "excretory",
      "protein synthesis"
    ],
    "correct": "antiphagocytic"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacterial capsule :",
    "options": [
      "is a virulence  factor",
      "is an organelle of locomotion",
      "is an obligatory structure",
      "is an extrachromosomal genetic component",
      "possesses the properties of an exotoxin"
    ],
    "correct": "is a virulence  factor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cytoplasmic bacterial inclusions are :",
    "options": [
      "stored nutrients",
      "extrachromosomal DNA",
      "endosymbionts",
      "intracellular parasites",
      "transposons"
    ],
    "correct": "stored nutrients"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microorganisms have an axostyle?",
    "options": [
      "spirochetes",
      "rickettsia",
      "actinomyces",
      "mycoplasma",
      "viruses"
    ],
    "correct": "spirochetes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which morphological properties do s pirochetes  have:",
    "options": [
      "a helically coiled shape",
      "they are diplobacteria",
      "they branching bacteria",
      "they are gram -positive"
    ],
    "correct": "a helically coiled shape"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which morphological properties do spirochetes  have:",
    "options": [
      "they are gram -negative",
      "they are diplobacteria",
      "they are gram -positive",
      "they branching bacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "they are gram -negative"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these types of motion are characteristic of s pirochetes  except :",
    "options": [
      "saltation (jump -like)",
      "rotation",
      "flexing",
      "stepwise",
      "cork-screw motion"
    ],
    "correct": "saltation (jump -like)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Borrelia have :",
    "options": [
      "3–8 large coils",
      "8–12 small coils",
      "more than  20 equal -size coils",
      "2–3 large coils",
      "½ coil"
    ],
    "correct": "3–8 large coils"
  },
  {
    "question": "The order Spirochaetales  does not include the genus :",
    "options": [
      "Rickettsia",
      "Treponema",
      "Borrelia",
      "Leptospira"
    ],
    "correct": "Rickettsia"
  },
  {
    "question": "The characteristic feature of all spirochetes is :",
    "options": [
      "motility",
      "they are obligate intracellular parasites",
      "the absence of peptidoglycan",
      "they are cell membrane parasites"
    ],
    "correct": "motility"
  },
  {
    "question": "The characteristic feature of mycoplasma is :",
    "options": [
      "the absence of the cell wall",
      "they are not fastidious",
      "they are the largest among prokaryotic microorganisms",
      "they are not capable of independent metabolism and reproduction",
      "a stable  shape"
    ],
    "correct": "the absence of the cell wall"
  },
  {
    "question": "The characteristic feature of chlamydia is :",
    "options": [
      "they are obligate intracellular parasites",
      "they have volutin granules",
      "they are eukaryotes",
      "they have axial filaments"
    ],
    "correct": "they are obligate intracellular parasites"
  },
  {
    "question": "Outside the host cells chlamydia exists as :",
    "options": [
      "elementary bodies",
      "initial bodies",
      "reticular bodies",
      "chromatin granules",
      "Which prokaryotes are obligate intracellular parasites and cannot synthesize ATP thus getting energy only from"
    ],
    "correct": "elementary bodies"
  },
  {
    "question": "a host cell :",
    "options": [
      "chlamydia",
      "actinomyces",
      "rickettsia",
      "mycoplasma",
      "spirochetes"
    ],
    "correct": "chlamydia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Obligate intracellular parasites include :",
    "options": [
      "chlamydia",
      "bacilli",
      "actinomyces",
      "meningococci",
      "mycoplasma"
    ],
    "correct": "chlamydia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Obligate intracellular parasites include :",
    "options": [
      "rickettsia",
      "clostridia",
      "listeria",
      "gonococci",
      "L-form bacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "rickettsia"
  },
  {
    "question": "The characteristic feature of rickettsia is :",
    "options": [
      "they are gram -negative",
      "they are coccus -shaped",
      "they are eukaryotes",
      "they are able to form a capsule",
      "they are motile thanks to their flagella"
    ],
    "correct": "they are gram -negative"
  },
  {
    "question": "What  is not characteristic  of rickettsia ?",
    "options": [
      "they grow on simple growth media",
      "they are obligate intracellular parasites",
      "they are prokaryotes",
      "they take up the red dye when stained by Zdrodovsky’s method",
      "they are polymorphic"
    ],
    "correct": "they grow on simple growth media"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mycoplasma differ from L-form bacteria as they do not have :",
    "options": [
      "a genetic  programme  of the cell wall synthesis",
      "chromosomes",
      "histones",
      "a phenotypic character – the cell wall",
      "a capacity to reproduce in the organism"
    ],
    "correct": "a genetic  programme  of the cell wall synthesis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which prokaryotes  form druses in an affected organism?",
    "options": [
      "actinomyces",
      "mycoplasma",
      "chlamydia",
      "rickettsia",
      "listeria"
    ],
    "correct": "actinomyces"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  microorganisms  are acellular ?",
    "options": [
      "viruses",
      "prokaryotes",
      "protozoa",
      "fungi",
      "algae"
    ],
    "correct": "viruses"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these factors influence the growth of pathogenic bacteria  except :",
    "options": [
      "light",
      "oxygen concentration",
      "the presence of growth factors",
      "carbon dioxide concentration",
      "temperature"
    ],
    "correct": "light"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteria  multiply by :",
    "options": [
      "transverse fission",
      "longitudinal fission",
      "replication",
      "exospores",
      "filterable forms"
    ],
    "correct": "transverse fission"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which structural component is characteristic of viruses?",
    "options": [
      "capsid",
      "differential nucleus",
      "ribosome",
      "the plasma membrane",
      "inclusions"
    ],
    "correct": "capsid"
  },
  {
    "question": "What  is the distinguishing  feature  of complex  viruses ?",
    "options": [
      "the presence of a viral envelope",
      "the presence of plus-strand RNA",
      "formation of a capsid",
      "presence of a core"
    ],
    "correct": "the presence of a viral envelope"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which viruses  are resistant to ether?",
    "options": [
      "the ones which do not have a viral envelope",
      "RNA -containing",
      "the ones which have a viral envelope",
      "DNA -containing"
    ],
    "correct": "the ones which do not have a viral envelope"
  },
  {
    "question": "The microorganisms which use organic substance as the source of energy and carbon are known as :",
    "options": [
      "chemoheterotrophs",
      "chemolit hoheterotrophs",
      "phototrophs",
      "photolit hotrophs",
      "autotrophs"
    ],
    "correct": "chemoheterotrophs"
  },
  {
    "question": "The microorganisms which need growth factors in addition to the basic source of carbon are known as :",
    "options": [
      "auxotrophs",
      "autotrophs",
      "prototrophs",
      "heterotrophs",
      "lithotrophs"
    ],
    "correct": "auxotrophs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which nutrition -based type of microorganisms is clinically significant?",
    "options": [
      "chemoheteroorganotrophs",
      "photoheterotrophs",
      "chemoautotrophs",
      "photoautotrophs",
      "facultative anaerobes"
    ],
    "correct": "chemoheteroorganotrophs"
  },
  {
    "question": "The demand of microorganisms in growth factors is:",
    "options": [
      "auxotrophy",
      "aerotolerance",
      "parasitism",
      "prototrophy",
      "infectivity"
    ],
    "correct": "auxotrophy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Clinically significant species of microorganisms are mostly :",
    "options": [
      "auxotrophs",
      "anaerobes",
      "metatrophs",
      "phototrophs",
      "autotrophs"
    ],
    "correct": "auxotrophs"
  },
  {
    "question": "The transfer of nutrients into a bacteria l cell  is carried out by all these ways of transport  except :",
    "options": [
      "simple  transport",
      "simple  diffusion",
      "facilitated  diffusion",
      "active transport",
      "group translocation"
    ],
    "correct": "simple  transport"
  },
  {
    "question": "The transport of substances into a bacteria l cell which does not require energy is :",
    "options": [
      "simple diffusion",
      "active transport",
      "group translocation",
      "phagocytosis",
      "endocytosis"
    ],
    "correct": "simple diffusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of transport requires the participation of perme ases?",
    "options": [
      "facilitated  diffusion",
      "active  transport",
      "passive  diffusion",
      "pinocytosis"
    ],
    "correct": "facilitated  diffusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  type of transport  requires  the participation  of permeases ?",
    "options": [
      "translocation of radicals",
      "active transport",
      "passive diffusion",
      "phagocytosis"
    ],
    "correct": "translocation of radicals"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteria  multiply  by:",
    "options": [
      "binary fission",
      "mitosis",
      "meiosis",
      "reproduction",
      "longitudinal fission"
    ],
    "correct": "binary fission"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteria  multiply  by:",
    "options": [
      "binary  fission",
      "replication",
      "spore  formation",
      "apoptosis",
      "L-form transformation"
    ],
    "correct": "binary  fission"
  },
  {
    "question": "The majority of  bacteria  multiply by :",
    "options": [
      "simple division of a cell",
      "sexual reproduction",
      "vegetative reproduction",
      "spore formation",
      "budding"
    ],
    "correct": "simple division of a cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which process occurs during the lag phase of a bacterial population growth?",
    "options": [
      "the balancing between the reproduction rate and death rate",
      "a fast reproduction of microorganisms",
      "the adaption of microorganisms to the  growth medium",
      "a fast death of microorganisms",
      "a slow growth of microorganisms"
    ],
    "correct": "the balancing between the reproduction rate and death rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteria  are biochemically active mostly during the :",
    "options": [
      "log phase  (exponential )",
      "lag phase",
      "stationary  phase",
      "death  phase",
      "spore  formation  phase"
    ],
    "correct": "log phase  (exponential )"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteria  are antibiotic  sensitive mostly during the :",
    "options": [
      "log phase  (exponential )",
      "lag phase",
      "stationary  phase",
      "death  phase",
      "spore  formation  phase"
    ],
    "correct": "log phase  (exponential )"
  },
  {
    "question": "According  to the optimum growth temperature  microorganisms can be all these  except :",
    "options": [
      "piezophiles",
      "mesophiles",
      "psych rophiles",
      "thermophiles"
    ],
    "correct": "piezophiles"
  },
  {
    "question": "The majority of pathogenic mesophilic bacteria  grow at temperature :",
    "options": [
      "30–37 °С",
      "15–20 °С",
      "20–30 °С",
      "50–55 °С",
      "25–30 °С"
    ],
    "correct": "30–37 °С"
  },
  {
    "question": "The optimum  temperature  for the culturing  of most clinically significant  bacteria is :",
    "options": [
      "37 ° С",
      "10 °С",
      "22 °С",
      "28 °С",
      "45 °С"
    ],
    "correct": "37 ° С"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which types of microorganisms are clinically significant?",
    "options": [
      "mesophiles",
      "psychrophiles",
      "thermophiles",
      "saprophytes",
      "archaea"
    ],
    "correct": "mesophiles"
  },
  {
    "question": "The type of metabolism of obligate anaerobes is :",
    "options": [
      "fermentative",
      "oxidative",
      "inducible",
      "constitutive"
    ],
    "correct": "fermentative"
  },
  {
    "question": "The type of metabolism of most clinically significant mi croorganism species is :",
    "options": [
      "oxidative, fermentative",
      "only oxidative",
      "only fermentative",
      "inducible",
      "constitutive"
    ],
    "correct": "oxidative, fermentative"
  },
  {
    "question": "The microorganisms  which  can grow  both with and without  oxygen  are:",
    "options": [
      "facultative  anaerobes",
      "obligate  aerobes",
      "obligate  anaerobes",
      "capnophiles",
      "microaerophil es"
    ],
    "correct": "facultative  anaerobes"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the type of respiration clinically significant microorganisms are mostly :",
    "options": [
      "facultative  anaerobes",
      "microaerophiles",
      "obligate  anaerobes",
      "obligate  aerobes",
      "lithotrophs"
    ],
    "correct": "facultative  anaerobes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What  are the requirements  for the culturing of microaerophiles?",
    "options": [
      "low concentration  of oxygen  and increased  level of carbon dioxide",
      "growth media containing antibiotics",
      "growth media containing human blood",
      "anaerobic  conditions",
      "growth media with low  рН"
    ],
    "correct": "low concentration  of oxygen  and increased  level of carbon dioxide"
  },
  {
    "question": "2lower than its concentration in the air?",
    "options": [
      "microaerophiles",
      "strict aerobes",
      "strict  anaerobes",
      "facultative  anaerobes",
      "auxotrophs"
    ],
    "correct": "microaerophiles"
  },
  {
    "question": "2is called :",
    "options": [
      "aerotolerance",
      "lipophilicity",
      "auxotrophy",
      "prototrophy",
      "saprotrophy"
    ],
    "correct": "aerotolerance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which conditions are required  to culture anaerobic bacteria ?",
    "options": [
      "the absence of oxygen in the air",
      "a complete absence of light",
      "the presence of  10%  of carbon dioxide in the air",
      "the presence of nitrogen",
      "the presence of 5% of oxygen in the air"
    ],
    "correct": "the absence of oxygen in the air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which physical method is used to create anaerobic conditions?",
    "options": [
      "anaerobic jar",
      "gas-generating sachets",
      "Fortner method",
      "thermostat",
      "Kitt-Tarozzi medium"
    ],
    "correct": "anaerobic jar"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the basic requirement for the isolation of anaerobes pure culture?",
    "options": [
      "using an anaerobic jar",
      "using complex growth media",
      "the proper culturing time",
      "optimum temperature"
    ],
    "correct": "using an anaerobic jar"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microorganisms are o bligate  anaerobes ?",
    "options": [
      "clostridia",
      "staphylococci",
      "pseudomonas",
      "enterobacteria",
      "bacilli"
    ],
    "correct": "clostridia"
  },
  {
    "question": "molecular  oxygen?",
    "options": [
      "strict  anaerobes",
      "facultative  anaerobes",
      "aerobes",
      "microaerophiles"
    ],
    "correct": "strict  anaerobes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  groups  of bacteria l enzymes  catalyze  intramolecular  conversions ?",
    "options": [
      "isomerase s",
      "glucosidase s",
      "carboxylase s",
      "dehydrogenase s"
    ],
    "correct": "isomerase s"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  group  of enzymes  do anaerobic  bacteria  lack?",
    "options": [
      "superoxi de dismutase s",
      "dehydrogenase s",
      "flavoprotein s",
      "lecithinases",
      "Which  enzymes  are being  constantly  synthesized  in a cell and are not dependent  on the presence  of a specific"
    ],
    "correct": "superoxi de dismutase s"
  },
  {
    "question": "substrate?",
    "options": [
      "constitutive  enzymes",
      "inducible   (adaptive)  enzymes",
      "endoenzymes",
      "exoenzymes",
      "invasive  enzymes"
    ],
    "correct": "constitutive  enzymes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The synthesis of these enzymes depends on the presence of a substrate :",
    "options": [
      "inducible  (adaptive)",
      "constitutive",
      "exoenzymes",
      "endoenzymes",
      "substrate"
    ],
    "correct": "inducible  (adaptive)"
  },
  {
    "question": "this enzyme :",
    "options": [
      "hyaluronidase",
      "plasma coagulase",
      "lecithinase",
      "neuraminidase",
      "integrase"
    ],
    "correct": "hyaluronidase"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cultural properties of bacteria  do not include :",
    "options": [
      "the shape of the cells of microorganisms",
      "the size of a colony",
      "the margin of a colony",
      "the surface of a colony",
      "the colour of a colony"
    ],
    "correct": "the shape of the cells of microorganisms"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a cultural property of a bacteria l pure culture?",
    "options": [
      "the appearance of a colony",
      "the shape of the cells of microorganisms",
      "tinctorial properties",
      "the combination of the cells of microorganisms"
    ],
    "correct": "the appearance of a colony"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a cultural property of a bacteria l pure culture?",
    "options": [
      "the margin of a colony",
      "the shape of the cells of microorganisms",
      "tinctorial  properties",
      "growth  rate",
      "All of these except  one are the requirements for collecting a test sample for bacteriological testing. Choose  the"
    ],
    "correct": "the margin of a colony"
  },
  {
    "question": "one which  is not correct :",
    "options": [
      "if a test sample cannot be delivered to the laboratory promptly it should be frozen",
      "a test sample is taken from affected areas and adjacent tissues",
      "a test sample is placed into a sterile laboratory container",
      "a test sample should be taken before antimicrobial therapy",
      "a test sample should be sent to the laboratory immediately"
    ],
    "correct": "if a test sample cannot be delivered to the laboratory promptly it should be frozen"
  },
  {
    "question": "The choice  of a test sample  for a bacteriological culture depends on :",
    "options": [
      "the clinical manifestations and pathogenesis of a disease",
      "a patient’s complaints",
      "the capacity of a laboratory",
      "the severity of a disease",
      "a doctor ’s skills"
    ],
    "correct": "the clinical manifestations and pathogenesis of a disease"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bacteri ological culture method is used in surgery :",
    "options": [
      "to monitor  the pathogens  causing suppurative inflammatory complications as well as their antibiotic resistance",
      "to prevent  infections  among  the medical staff",
      "for screen ing in a healthcare facility",
      "to study the microbial landscape of environmental objects",
      "for sanitary  and bacteri ological screening of visitors"
    ],
    "correct": "to monitor  the pathogens  causing suppurative inflammatory complications as well as their antibiotic resistance"
  },
  {
    "question": "The method which is used for the isolation and identification of pure  bacteria l culture is a :",
    "options": [
      "bacteri ological (microbial) culture  method",
      "biological method",
      "serological method",
      "microscopy  method",
      "molecular -biological method"
    ],
    "correct": "bacteri ological (microbial) culture  method"
  },
  {
    "question": "The growth media in microbiology are used for everything except  (choose the wrong answer) :",
    "options": [
      "to determine the immunogram",
      "to culture microorganisms",
      "to study the biochemical properties of microorganisms",
      "to preserve  archival  cultures  of microorganisms",
      "to deter mine  the antibiotic  sensitivity of cultures"
    ],
    "correct": "to determine the immunogram"
  },
  {
    "question": "The choice of growth media for microbial cultures depends on the :",
    "options": [
      "physiology of microorganisms",
      "antigenic structure of microorganisms",
      "phage sensitivity of microorganisms",
      "morphology of microorganisms",
      "virulence of  microorganisms"
    ],
    "correct": "physiology of microorganisms"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these techniques are used to isolate a pure culture except  one (choose the wrong one) :",
    "options": [
      "a lawn  culture",
      "streaking",
      "a microbial culture on selective growth media",
      "infecting susceptible laboratory animals",
      "heating a test sample to isolate b acilli"
    ],
    "correct": "a lawn  culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aim of the bacterial  culture  method in the diagnosing procedure is:",
    "options": [
      "isolation  and identification  of a pure culture and determining its antibiotic sensitivity",
      "detection and identification of a pathogen",
      "determination of the virulence of a pathogen",
      "determination of the immunity level",
      "separation of microbial cells"
    ],
    "correct": "isolation  and identification  of a pure culture and determining its antibiotic sensitivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "used?",
    "options": [
      "serum",
      "sputum",
      "blood",
      "pus",
      "urine"
    ],
    "correct": "serum"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aim of the 1 -st stage of the bacterial culture (bacteriological) method is :",
    "options": [
      "growing isolated colonies",
      "the inoculation of a test sample",
      "the microscopy of a test sample",
      "identification of a culture",
      "enrichment of a pure culture"
    ],
    "correct": "growing isolated colonies"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technique is used to determine the amount of bacteri a in a test sample?",
    "options": [
      "serial dilutio n",
      "inoculation with a streaking rod",
      "a biological method",
      "Fortner  method"
    ],
    "correct": "serial dilutio n"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  method  of a pure culture isolation does not include mechanical separation ?",
    "options": [
      "a biological models method",
      "innoculation with a streaking rod",
      "a streaking culture",
      "Koch method (serial dilution)"
    ],
    "correct": "a biological models method"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aim of the 2 -nd stage of the bacterial culture (bacteriological) method is :",
    "options": [
      "enrichment (accumulation) of a pure culture",
      "identification of a pure culture",
      "examining the biochemical activity",
      "determining the antibiotic sensitivity of a test culture",
      "bacteria l typing"
    ],
    "correct": "enrichment (accumulation) of a pure culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aim of passaging isolated colonies to an agar slant is :",
    "options": [
      "accumulation of a pure culture",
      "identification of  bacteri a",
      "separation  of bacteri a",
      "growing isolated colonies",
      "accumulation of anaerobic  bacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "accumulation of a pure culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aim of the 3 -rd stage of the bacterial culture (bacteriological) method is :",
    "options": [
      "identification of a pure culture",
      "growing isolated colonies",
      "detection of a pathogen in a test sample",
      "accumulation of a test culture",
      "determining the purity  of an isolated culture"
    ],
    "correct": "identification of a pure culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "The necessary condition for the identification of an isolated culture is :",
    "options": [
      "the purity of a culture",
      "the presence of a culture",
      "the availability of required growth media in a laboratory",
      "a patient’s condition",
      "a doctor’s recomendation"
    ],
    "correct": "the purity of a culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "except :",
    "options": [
      "isolation of  a pure culture",
      "the examination of the purity of an isolated culture",
      "the examination of a biochemical activity",
      "the determination of motility",
      "the determination of the antibiotic sensitivity"
    ],
    "correct": "isolation of  a pure culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "except :",
    "options": [
      "the determination of a genotype",
      "the identification of a pure culture",
      "the determination of a serotype",
      "the determination of motility",
      "the determination of phagovar"
    ],
    "correct": "the determination of a genotype"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aim of microscopy during the 3 -rd stage of the bacterial culture (bacteriological ) method  is to determine :",
    "options": [
      "morphological and tinctorial homogeneity",
      "virulence",
      "antigenic properties",
      "biochemical activity",
      "a genotype"
    ],
    "correct": "morphological and tinctorial homogeneity"
  },
  {
    "question": "The smears taken from isolated colonies are examined under the microscope in order to :",
    "options": [
      "study morphological and tinctorial properties",
      "study cultural properties",
      "determine a genotype",
      "determine the phagovar of an isolated culture",
      "determine the bacteriocin sensitivity"
    ],
    "correct": "study morphological and tinctorial properties"
  },
  {
    "question": "and toxigenic properties?",
    "options": [
      "3-rd",
      "1-st",
      "2-nd",
      "4-th"
    ],
    "correct": "3-rd"
  },
  {
    "question": "The determination of the antibiotic sensitivity and resistance of cultures is performed because :",
    "options": [
      "microorganisms have acquired drug resistance",
      "microorganisms have a natural drug resistance",
      "new antibiotics have been produced",
      "there is a possibilit y of complications",
      "a patient wants this"
    ],
    "correct": "microorganisms have acquired drug resistance"
  },
  {
    "question": "The microbiological aim of the antibiotic resistance examination  is to:",
    "options": [
      "determine an acquired resistance",
      "identify a culture",
      "determine the spectrum of activity of a drug",
      "determine the long -range efficacy of treatme nt",
      "determine  natural  resistance"
    ],
    "correct": "determine an acquired resistance"
  },
  {
    "question": "The clinical  aim of the antibiotic resistance examination is to :",
    "options": [
      "determine the long -range efficacy of treatment",
      "determine the purchase volume of medicinal drugs",
      "choose the route of a medication administration",
      "choose the dosage of a medicinal drug",
      "determine  natural  resistance"
    ],
    "correct": "determine the long -range efficacy of treatment"
  },
  {
    "question": "The result of the bacterial culture (bacteriological) testing is given by the bacteriological laboratory :",
    "options": [
      "on the 4-5-th day",
      "within 1-2 hours",
      "on the 2-nd or 3-rd day",
      "on the 3-rd or 4-th day",
      "on the 7-10-th day"
    ],
    "correct": "on the 4-5-th day"
  },
  {
    "question": "The time of the bacterial  culture  (bacteriological ) testing  result  depends  on:",
    "options": [
      "the generation time of a pathogen",
      "the time of collecting samples",
      "the duration of samples delivery",
      "the financial capability of a laboratory",
      "the professional competence of the staff"
    ],
    "correct": "the generation time of a pathogen"
  },
  {
    "question": "The determination of bacterial biochemical activity implies :",
    "options": [
      "determining  intermediate and final metabolic products",
      "separation of microbial cells",
      "culturing in Hiss sugar media",
      "culturing in meat -peptone broth",
      "selecting a growth medium"
    ],
    "correct": "determining  intermediate and final metabolic products"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is not used to examine  the biochemical properties of microorganisms ?",
    "options": [
      "cell culture",
      "Hiss sugar media",
      "multitest media",
      "differential  diagnostic  media"
    ],
    "correct": "cell culture"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  requirement  should synthetic growth media comply with?",
    "options": [
      "optimal рH",
      "the presence of agar-agar",
      "the presence of blood serum",
      "the presence of an indicator"
    ],
    "correct": "optimal рH"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which requirement should synthetic growth media comply with?",
    "options": [
      "isotonicity",
      "the absence of oxygen",
      "the presence of antibiotics",
      "stability"
    ],
    "correct": "isotonicity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which requirement should synthetic growth media comply with?",
    "options": [
      "sterility",
      "the presence of native proteins",
      "selectivity",
      "saturation with oxygen"
    ],
    "correct": "sterility"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which growth media are used to produce isolated colonies by inoculating  test material ?",
    "options": [
      "solid",
      "liquid",
      "dry",
      "semi -solid ( semi-liquid )"
    ],
    "correct": "solid"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are the characteristics of microbial growth in liquid growth media except :",
    "options": [
      "the growth of isolated colonies",
      "diffuse turbidity",
      "biofilms on the surface of a growth medium",
      "the bottom growth",
      "the growth on the walls of a test -tube"
    ],
    "correct": "the growth of isolated colonies"
  },
  {
    "question": "R-colonies of bacteria are :",
    "options": [
      "rough",
      "smooth",
      "slimy (mucous)",
      "regular",
      "pigmented"
    ],
    "correct": "rough"
  },
  {
    "question": "S-colonies of bacteria are :",
    "options": [
      "smooth",
      "bumpy",
      "rough",
      "dry",
      "pigmented"
    ],
    "correct": "smooth"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which growth media are used to isolate the pure culture of a  certain pathogen?",
    "options": [
      "selective",
      "multi -purpose",
      "differential diagnostic",
      "simple",
      "transport"
    ],
    "correct": "selective"
  },
  {
    "question": "others?",
    "options": [
      "enrichment growth media",
      "differential diagnostic",
      "multi-purpose",
      "simple",
      "transport"
    ],
    "correct": "enrichment growth media"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which growth media stimulate a fast and massive growth of one microbial species?",
    "options": [
      "enrichment growth media",
      "differential diagnostic growth media",
      "meat -peptone agar",
      "basic growth media",
      "blood  agar"
    ],
    "correct": "enrichment growth media"
  },
  {
    "question": "The basic  components  of a differential  diagnostic  growth  medium  are:",
    "options": [
      "indicator , a chemical substrate in relation to which microorganisms are distinguished , meat -peptone  agar",
      "indicator , a selective factor to determine a certain bacterial species , meat -peptone  agar",
      "indicator , serum , meat -peptone  agar",
      "indicator , antibiotics , a chemical substrate in relation to which microorganisms are distinguished"
    ],
    "correct": "indicator , a chemical substrate in relation to which microorganisms are distinguished , meat -peptone  agar"
  },
  {
    "question": "The preserving growth medium is used :",
    "options": [
      "to prevent the death of pathogenic bacteria  and inhibit the growth of saprophytes",
      "for the first culturing of the material",
      "for the indication of separate groups of bacteria",
      "to accumulate a particular  group of bacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "to prevent the death of pathogenic bacteria  and inhibit the growth of saprophytes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The enrichment growth medium is used :",
    "options": [
      "to accumulate a particular group of bacteria",
      "for the first culturing of the material",
      "for the indication of separate groups of bacteria",
      "to prevent the death of pathogenic bacteria  and inhibit the growth of saprophytes"
    ],
    "correct": "to accumulate a particular group of bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "The selective growth medium is used :",
    "options": [
      "for the first culturing of the material or for the subculturing of the material taken f rom preserving or",
      "enrichment growth media",
      "for the indication of separate groups of bacteria",
      "to prevent the death of pathogenic bacteria  and inhibit the growth of saprophytes",
      "to accumulate a particular group of bacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "for the first culturing of the material or for the subculturing of the material taken f rom preserving or"
  },
  {
    "question": "The differential growth medium is used:",
    "options": [
      "for the indication of separate groups of bacteria",
      "for the first culturing of the material",
      "to prevent the death of pathogenic bacteria  and inhibit the growth of saprophytes",
      "to accumulate a particular group of bacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "for the indication of separate groups of bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Endo  agar is used:",
    "options": [
      "to examine  the saccharolytic  properties of bacteria",
      "as an enrichment growth med ium",
      "as a growth medium  to accumulate bacteria",
      "for the identification of a diphtheria agent",
      "to determine motility"
    ],
    "correct": "to examine  the saccharolytic  properties of bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "A semi -liquid  (semi-solid ) agar is used:",
    "options": [
      "to determine motility",
      "to examine  the saccharolytic  properties of bacteria",
      "as an enrichment growth med ium",
      "as a growth medium  to accumulate bacteria",
      "for the identification of a diphtheria agent"
    ],
    "correct": "to determine motility"
  },
  {
    "question": "Liquid growth media include:",
    "options": [
      "meat -peptone broth",
      "meat -peptone agar",
      "Endo agar",
      "blood agar",
      "salt egg -yolk agar"
    ],
    "correct": "meat -peptone broth"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are types of growth media differentiated according to their purpose except :",
    "options": [
      "blood medium",
      "differential diagnostic",
      "transport",
      "selective",
      "enrichment medium"
    ],
    "correct": "blood medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Blood agar is :",
    "options": [
      "used to determine the hemolytic activity of bacteria",
      "blood serum",
      "a differential diagnostic growth medium",
      "a selective growth medium",
      "hemolyzed blood"
    ],
    "correct": "used to determine the hemolytic activity of bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which growth media is used to determine the hemolytic properties of bacteria?",
    "options": [
      "blood agar",
      "bismuth sulfite agar",
      "salt egg -yolk agar",
      "Levin  medium",
      "Endo  agar"
    ],
    "correct": "blood agar"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is used to detect plasma coagulase?",
    "options": [
      "citrate plasma",
      "rabbit plasma",
      "blood",
      "egg yolk"
    ],
    "correct": "citrate plasma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  growth  medium  is used to detect  lecithinase  of staphylococci :",
    "options": [
      "salt egg -yolk agar",
      "blood agar",
      "milk-salt agar",
      "salt agar"
    ],
    "correct": "salt egg -yolk agar"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are differential diagnostic growth media used for?",
    "options": [
      "to examine the properties of certain bacteria",
      "to inhibit the growth of saprophytes",
      "to stimulate the growth of a certain species of bacteria while inhibiting the growth of others",
      "to accumulate  bacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "to examine the properties of certain bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "What  indicates  the saccharolytic activity of bacteria ?",
    "options": [
      "the formation of acidic and gaseous metabolic products",
      "the presence of growth",
      "the type of growth",
      "the formation of alkaline and gaseous metabolic products",
      "the formation of neutral and gaseous metabolic products"
    ],
    "correct": "the formation of acidic and gaseous metabolic products"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which growth medium is used to determine the saccharolytic activity of microorganisms?",
    "options": [
      "Hiss media",
      "blood agar",
      "meat -peptone agar",
      "meat -peptone broth",
      "salt egg -yolk agar"
    ],
    "correct": "Hiss media"
  },
  {
    "question": "production of  acid?",
    "options": [
      "the change in the colour  of the  indicator in the medium",
      "gas bubbles emission in the semi -solid medium",
      "the change in the colour of the indicator  and gas bubbles emission",
      "the colour of the medium remains unchanged, gas bubbles are not emitted",
      "turbidi ty of the medium and precipitate formation"
    ],
    "correct": "the change in the colour  of the  indicator in the medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Chemically  enzymes  are:",
    "options": [
      "metabolites",
      "substrates",
      "isotopes",
      "cofactors",
      "prions"
    ],
    "correct": "metabolites"
  },
  {
    "question": "The differentiative  factor of salt egg -yolk agar is :",
    "options": [
      "lecithin",
      "the salts of bile acids",
      "10 % NaCl",
      "lactose",
      "sucrose"
    ],
    "correct": "lecithin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which growth medium is often used to isolate no -fastidious ba cteria ?",
    "options": [
      "meat -peptone agar",
      "Bordet -Gengou agar",
      "salt egg-yolk agar",
      "casein -charcoal  acid",
      "serum agar"
    ],
    "correct": "meat -peptone agar"
  },
  {
    "question": "The differentiative  factor of Endo agar is :",
    "options": [
      "lactose",
      "glucose",
      "maltose",
      "fructose",
      "mannitol"
    ],
    "correct": "lactose"
  },
  {
    "question": "The growth  of colorless  colonies  on Endo  agar proves  that the microorganism  cannot :",
    "options": [
      "ferment  lactose",
      "ferment  glucose",
      "produce  indole",
      "produce  hydrogen  sulfid e",
      "produce  ammonia"
    ],
    "correct": "ferment  lactose"
  },
  {
    "question": "The growth  of blue colonies  on Levine  growth  medium  proves that microorganism can :",
    "options": [
      "ferment  lactose",
      "ferment  glucose",
      "produce  H2S",
      "produce  indole",
      "produce  ammonia"
    ],
    "correct": "ferment  lactose"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which phenomenon indicates the proteolytic properties of bacteria  on meat -peptone broth?",
    "options": [
      "production of hydrogen sulfide and indole",
      "producti on of amino acids",
      "the presence  and type of growth",
      "formation of acidic metabolic products",
      "production of proteases"
    ],
    "correct": "production of hydrogen sulfide and indole"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  growth  medium  is used to culture  obligate  anaerobes?",
    "options": [
      "Wilson -Blair agar",
      "bile broth",
      "Endo agar",
      "selenite broth",
      "Ploskirev medium"
    ],
    "correct": "Wilson -Blair agar"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which growth medium is used to accumulate a pure culture of  anaerobes?",
    "options": [
      "thioglycollate medium",
      "Zeissler blood agar",
      "meat -peptone  agar",
      "meat -peptone  broth"
    ],
    "correct": "thioglycollate medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which growth medium is used to culture anaerobes?",
    "options": [
      "Kitt-Tarozzi medium",
      "salt egg-yolk agar",
      "peptone  water",
      "Endo  agar",
      "Clauberg agar"
    ],
    "correct": "Kitt-Tarozzi medium"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are growth media used for culturing anaerobes except:",
    "options": [
      "bile broth",
      "Kitt-Tarozzi  medium",
      "thioglycollate medium",
      "Wilson -Blair  agar"
    ],
    "correct": "bile broth"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  of those  methods  does not provide a complete sterilization of an object?",
    "options": [
      "pasteurization",
      "gamma radiation",
      "dry heat",
      "autoclaving",
      "calcination"
    ],
    "correct": "pasteurization"
  },
  {
    "question": "Simple  growth  media  are sterilized  by:",
    "options": [
      "sterilization with steam under pressure in an autoclave",
      "calcination",
      "tyndallization",
      "dry heat",
      "pasteurization"
    ],
    "correct": "sterilization with steam under pressure in an autoclave"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sera are sterilized  by:",
    "options": [
      "tyndallization",
      "calcination",
      "boiling",
      "dry heat",
      "autoclaving"
    ],
    "correct": "tyndallization"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal human microflora :",
    "options": [
      "is numerous",
      "is formed during the prenatal development",
      "is present in all organs and tissues",
      "includes only prokaryotes",
      "does not change during lifetime"
    ],
    "correct": "is numerous"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal human microflora :",
    "options": [
      "produces biofilms",
      "is formed during the prenatal development",
      "is present in all organs and tissues",
      "includes only prokaryotes",
      "does not change during lifetime"
    ],
    "correct": "produces biofilms"
  },
  {
    "question": "The basic form of existence of normal microflora :",
    "options": [
      "a biofilm",
      "a nonculturable form",
      "an L-form",
      "a spore",
      "a hybridoma"
    ],
    "correct": "a biofilm"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are the properties of the microbes in a biofilm except :",
    "options": [
      "they disrupt the absorption of nutrients",
      "they form  microcolonies",
      "they are encapsulated in a polymeric matrix (glycocalyx)",
      "they are more resistant to antimicrobial drugs",
      "they have a system of connections"
    ],
    "correct": "they disrupt the absorption of nutrients"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are the causes of gastrointestinal dysbacteriosis (dysbiosis) except:",
    "options": [
      "consumption of probiotics",
      "gastrointestinal diseases",
      "endocrine disorders",
      "hormonal therapy",
      "antimicrobial therapy"
    ],
    "correct": "consumption of probiotics"
  },
  {
    "question": "A person should be tested for intestinal dysbacteriosis :",
    "options": [
      "if he suffers from a long -time intestinal dysfunction",
      "before entering an educational institution  (a kindergarten, a school, a university )",
      "if he works in the foodservice industry",
      "if he works in kindergartens and schools",
      "before donating blood"
    ],
    "correct": "if he suffers from a long -time intestinal dysfunction"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are the factors which contribute to the development of dysbiosis (dysbacteriosis) except :",
    "options": [
      "consumptions of vitamins",
      "infectious diseases",
      "chronic non -infectious diseases",
      "consumption of immunosuppressive drugs",
      "consumption of antibiotics"
    ],
    "correct": "consumptions of vitamins"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are the  exogenous  factors  which  influence  normal  human microflora (microbiota) except :",
    "options": [
      "gender",
      "consumption of antibiotics",
      "dietary pattern",
      "pollution of the environment",
      "drug addiction"
    ],
    "correct": "gender"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an  endogenous  factor  which  influences  normal  human microflora (microbiota) ?",
    "options": [
      "gender",
      "consumption of antibiotics",
      "dietary pattern",
      "season",
      "ecology"
    ],
    "correct": "gender"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are the functions of normal microflora except :",
    "options": [
      "formation of new species",
      "production of biologically active substances",
      "participation in the metabolism of  proteins, carbohydrates and lipids, etc.",
      "detoxification",
      "the pool of plasmid and chromosomal genes"
    ],
    "correct": "formation of new species"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is a positive function of normal microflora?",
    "options": [
      "antagonistic",
      "carcinogenic",
      "toxigenic",
      "mutagenic",
      "stimulation of autoimmune processes"
    ],
    "correct": "antagonistic"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are th e positive functions of normal human microflora except :",
    "options": [
      "toxigenic",
      "secretory",
      "antagonistic",
      "immunizing",
      "vitamin -producing"
    ],
    "correct": "toxigenic"
  },
  {
    "question": "The c olonization resistance of epithelium is provided by:",
    "options": [
      "normal  microflora",
      "pathogenic  microflora",
      "hemophilic  E.coli",
      "putrefactive microorganisms"
    ],
    "correct": "normal  microflora"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microbes participate in the formation of the colonization resistance of intestinal microflora?",
    "options": [
      "E.coli",
      "yeasts of the Candida  genus",
      "Proteus species",
      "Staphylococcus aureus"
    ],
    "correct": "E.coli"
  },
  {
    "question": "The negative role of normal microflora is :",
    "options": [
      "it causes autoinfect ions",
      "immunizing",
      "stimulation of lymphoid tissue formation",
      "anticarcinogenic",
      "antimutagenic"
    ],
    "correct": "it causes autoinfect ions"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal microflora in the large intestine of an adult includes all these microorganisms except :",
    "options": [
      "rickettsia",
      "bacteroides",
      "bifido bacteria",
      "enterococci",
      "enterobacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "rickettsia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microbes participate in the formation of the colonization resistance of intestinal microflora?",
    "options": [
      "non-sporeforming  anaerobes",
      "yeasts of the Candida  genus",
      "Proteus species",
      "Staphylococcus aureus"
    ],
    "correct": "non-sporeforming  anaerobes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which intestinal microflora prevails during the breast -feedi ng period?",
    "options": [
      "bifido bacteria",
      "staphylococci",
      "E.coli",
      "enterococci",
      "enterobacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "bifido bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal  intestinal  microflora of a baby during the breast -feeding period :",
    "options": [
      "includes bifido bacteria",
      "develops at the end of the first month",
      "is not sensitive to antibiotics",
      "includes thermophiles",
      "colonizes all the parts"
    ],
    "correct": "includes bifido bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "The formation of the normal microflora of a baby is determined by all these factors except :",
    "options": [
      "a type of anaesthetic  administered to a mother during  the childbirth",
      "the maturity of a fetus",
      "a method of delivery",
      "the microflora in a mother’s birth canals",
      "the type of feeding"
    ],
    "correct": "a type of anaesthetic  administered to a mother during  the childbirth"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these  are the risk factors  which can cause dysbacteri osis in newborn babies except :",
    "options": [
      "the first -time delivery",
      "bacteria l vaginosis of a mother",
      "late breast -feeding",
      "high-risk pregnancy",
      "premature delivery"
    ],
    "correct": "the first -time delivery"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these  are the risk factors  which can cause dys bacteri osis in toddlers except :",
    "options": [
      "probiotics administration",
      "immunodeficiency disorders",
      "early bottle -feeding",
      "an infectious pathology",
      "a somatic pathology"
    ],
    "correct": "probiotics administration"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal vaginal microflora depends on all these factors except :",
    "options": [
      "the body type",
      "the hormonal status",
      "age",
      "the type of contraception",
      "the phase of the menstrual"
    ],
    "correct": "the body type"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal  vaginal  microflora  includes  mostly :",
    "options": [
      "lacto bacilli",
      "bacteroides",
      "fusobacteria",
      "veillonellas",
      "mobiluncus"
    ],
    "correct": "lacto bacilli"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these microorganisms belong to the normal vaginal microflora except :",
    "options": [
      "clostridia",
      "lacto bacteria",
      "streptococci",
      "bacteroides"
    ],
    "correct": "clostridia"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are the factors which provide the protective role of the normal vaginal microflora except :",
    "options": [
      "phagocytosis  of pathogenic microorganisms",
      "blockage  of receptors",
      "production of antimicrobial substances",
      "induction of the immune response",
      "detoxification of xenobiotics"
    ],
    "correct": "phagocytosis  of pathogenic microorganisms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteria l vaginosis is :",
    "options": [
      "a non-inflammatory  syndrome related to vaginal dys bacteri osis",
      "a sexually -transmitted infection",
      "a highly contagious disease",
      "is inherited",
      "is a hospital -acquired infection"
    ],
    "correct": "a non-inflammatory  syndrome related to vaginal dys bacteri osis"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these conditions can be provoked by bacterial vaginosis except :",
    "options": [
      "cardio -vascular diseases",
      "the diseases of the uterus and epoophora",
      "pathological conditions during pregnancy",
      "activation of a viral infection",
      "sexually -transmitted infections"
    ],
    "correct": "cardio -vascular diseases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which technique is used during the diagnosing procedure of bacteria l vaginosis?",
    "options": [
      "microscopy",
      "bacteria l culture",
      "serology",
      "gas chromatography",
      "polymerase chain reactio n"
    ],
    "correct": "microscopy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which organ is normally sterile in a healthy person?",
    "options": [
      "lungs",
      "eye conjunctiva",
      "vagina",
      "nasopharynx",
      "small intestine"
    ],
    "correct": "lungs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which organ is normally sterile in a healthy person?",
    "options": [
      "uterus",
      "eye conjunctiva",
      "vagina",
      "nasopharynx",
      "small intestine"
    ],
    "correct": "uterus"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these microorganisms belong to the normal oral microflora except :",
    "options": [
      "gonococci",
      "streptococci",
      "actinomyc es",
      "veillonellas",
      "fusobacteria"
    ],
    "correct": "gonococci"
  },
  {
    "question": "The normal microflora of the upper respiratory tract includes :",
    "options": [
      "streptococci",
      "respiratory  viruses",
      "brucellas",
      "Vibrio  cholerae",
      "E.coli"
    ],
    "correct": "streptococci"
  },
  {
    "question": "The disruption  of the normal  intestinal  microflora  leads to :",
    "options": [
      "dysbacteri osis",
      "hypervitaminosis",
      "autoimmune diseases",
      "acute food poisoning",
      "the increase  of antibodies  titer"
    ],
    "correct": "dysbacteri osis"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are the  properties of normal  intestinal  microflora except :",
    "options": [
      "it includes mostly aerobes",
      "it determines the colonization resistance",
      "it has antagonistic properties",
      "it is the most numerous",
      "it is the most diverse"
    ],
    "correct": "it includes mostly aerobes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The basic  method of  dysbacteriosis  diagnosis is :",
    "options": [
      "bacterial culture ( bacteri ological)",
      "clinical",
      "biochemical",
      "chromatography"
    ],
    "correct": "bacterial culture ( bacteri ological)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which method of testing is used to diagnose intestinal dys bacteri osis?",
    "options": [
      "microbiological culture ( bacteri ological) method",
      "serological tests",
      "allergy tests",
      "laboratory animals testing",
      "a patient’s story"
    ],
    "correct": "microbiological culture ( bacteri ological) method"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the basis of dysbacteriosis treatment?",
    "options": [
      "elimination of the cause of dysbacteriosis",
      "immunoglobulins  intake",
      "a sensible antimicrobial therapy",
      "boosting the immunity",
      "a healthy diet"
    ],
    "correct": "elimination of the cause of dysbacteriosis"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these means are used to treat dysbacteriosis except  one, which one is wrong?",
    "options": [
      "antibioti cs",
      "probiotics",
      "prebiotics",
      "bacteriophage",
      "food products enriched with probiotics"
    ],
    "correct": "antibioti cs"
  },
  {
    "question": "Probiotics are :",
    "options": [
      "normal microflora species",
      "vaccines",
      "allergens",
      "vitamins",
      "bacteri ophages"
    ],
    "correct": "normal microflora species"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is the characteristic of b acteri ophages?",
    "options": [
      "they are obligate intracellular parasites",
      "they have a nucleus",
      "they have a cellular structure",
      "they have a bacterial origin",
      "they have intracellular inclusions"
    ],
    "correct": "they are obligate intracellular parasites"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteri ophages are :",
    "options": [
      "resistant to antibiotics",
      "gram -positive",
      "gram -negative",
      "fastidious",
      "pathogens which cause hospital -acquired infections"
    ],
    "correct": "resistant to antibiotics"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is the property of bacteri ophages?",
    "options": [
      "lytic or lysogenic activity",
      "the absence of specificity",
      "bacteria l nature",
      "cellular structure",
      "capacity for binary fission"
    ],
    "correct": "lytic or lysogenic activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  property of bacteri ophages enables their use in treatment and diagnosing procedures?",
    "options": [
      "specificity",
      "antigenicity",
      "immunogenicity",
      "virulence",
      "transmissibility"
    ],
    "correct": "specificity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the result of interaction between a virulent bacteriophage and a bacterial cell?",
    "options": [
      "lysis of a ba cterial cell",
      "lysogenization",
      "the increase of cell division rate",
      "formation of a defective bacteriophage",
      "phage conversion"
    ],
    "correct": "lysis of a ba cterial cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these  are the stages  of the interaction between virulent bacteriophages and a bacterial cell except :",
    "options": [
      "a log phase",
      "the adsorption of a bacteri ophage on a cell",
      "the penetration of a p hage nucleic acid into a bacterial cell",
      "the assembly of a bacteri ophage (morphogenesis )",
      "the exit of a  bacteri ophage from a host cell"
    ],
    "correct": "a log phase"
  },
  {
    "question": "The first stage of a virulent bacteriophage reproduction is :",
    "options": [
      "the adsorption of a bacteri ophage on a susceptible  cell",
      "the penetration  of a bacteri ophage into a host cell",
      "the injection of phage DNA into the  nucleoid  of a host cell",
      "the synthesis of the structural components of a bacteriophage",
      "the assembly of phage components"
    ],
    "correct": "the adsorption of a bacteri ophage on a susceptible  cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "The interaction between a temperate bacteriophage and a bacterial cell involves :",
    "options": [
      "the integration  of phage DNA with the genome of a cell",
      "chemotaxis",
      "adsorption of a phage on a  bacterial cell",
      "binary fission",
      "the exit of mature phages from a bacterial cell"
    ],
    "correct": "the integration  of phage DNA with the genome of a cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "The type of interaction between a temperate bacterio phage and a bacterial cell is :",
    "options": [
      "integrative",
      "abortive",
      "productive",
      "spontaneous",
      "induced"
    ],
    "correct": "integrative"
  },
  {
    "question": "The type of interaction between a virulent bacteriophage and a bacterial cell is :",
    "options": [
      "productive",
      "integrative",
      "abortive",
      "spontaneous",
      "induced"
    ],
    "correct": "productive"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacteriophages are cultured :",
    "options": [
      "in bacterial cultures",
      "in cell cultures",
      "in laboratory animals",
      "in chicken embryos",
      "on growth media"
    ],
    "correct": "in bacterial cultures"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which factor indicates the reproduction of virulent bacteriophages?",
    "options": [
      "the formation of negative colonies",
      "the positive result of the hemadsorption assay",
      "the turbidity in a growth medium",
      "the change of colour of a growth medium",
      "the growth of isolated colonies"
    ],
    "correct": "the formation of negative colonies"
  },
  {
    "question": "Diagnostic bacteriophages are used :",
    "options": [
      "for the identification of bacteria",
      "to treat infectious diseases",
      "for the prophylaxis of infectious diseases",
      "as immune drugs"
    ],
    "correct": "for the identification of bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "The transfer of genetic material from some bacteria to others with the help of phages is also known as :",
    "options": [
      "transduction",
      "transformation",
      "conjugation",
      "replication",
      "modification"
    ],
    "correct": "transduction"
  },
  {
    "question": "All these are the ways to use bacteriophages except one  (choose the wrong answer) :",
    "options": [
      "to determine the phagocytic activity",
      "for phage typing",
      "to determine the source and transmission factors of an infection",
      "in phage therapy",
      "for phage differentiation"
    ],
    "correct": "to determine the phagocytic activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which b acteri ophages are components of therapeutic and preventi ve drugs?",
    "options": [
      "virulent",
      "defective",
      "typical",
      "temperate",
      "conjugative"
    ],
    "correct": "virulent"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  exotoxin  inhibits  protein  synthesis ?",
    "options": [
      "diphtheria  toxin",
      "pneumolysin",
      "hemolysin",
      "cholera  toxin",
      "hyaluronidase"
    ],
    "correct": "diphtheria  toxin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one is a neurotoxin?",
    "options": [
      "botulinum toxin",
      "exfoliatin",
      "pneumolysin",
      "streptolysin O",
      "dermonecrotoxin"
    ],
    "correct": "botulinum toxin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Exotoxins are produced by :",
    "options": [
      "both gram -positive  and gram -negative  bacteria",
      "only gram -negative bacteria",
      "only gram -positive bacteria",
      "viruses",
      "prions"
    ],
    "correct": "both gram -positive  and gram -negative  bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bacterial exotoxins appear in the environment as a result of :",
    "options": [
      "the living activities of bacteria",
      "capsule formation",
      "spore formation",
      "destruction of bacteria",
      "unfavorable environmental conditions"
    ],
    "correct": "the living activities of bacteria"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which microorganisms produce endotoxins?",
    "options": [
      "gram -negative bacteria",
      "gram -positive bacteria",
      "both gram -positive  and gram -negative  bacteria",
      "viruses",
      "prions"
    ],
    "correct": "gram -negative bacteria"
  }
]